<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Three [morall] treatises no lesse pleasau[nt] than necessary for all men to read[e,] wherof the one is called the learned prince, the other the fruites of foes, the thyrde the porte of rest.</title>
            <title>Moralia. Selections. English</title>
            <author>Plutarch.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1561</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 141 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 69 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A09799</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 20063.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S110436</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99845980</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99845980</idno>
            <idno type="VID">176515</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A09799)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 176515)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 339:26)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Three [morall] treatises no lesse pleasau[nt] than necessary for all men to read[e,] wherof the one is called the learned prince, the other the fruites of foes, the thyrde the porte of rest.</title>
                  <title>Moralia. Selections. English</title>
                  <author>Plutarch.</author>
                  <author>Blundeville, Thomas, fl. 1561.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[140] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Wyllyam Seres, dwellynge at the west ende of Poules at the signe of the Hedghogge. Cum priuilegio ad imprimendum solum,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprynted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1561 (7 June)]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>By Plutarch, whose name appears on ¹A2r.</note>
                  <note>A translation of selections from: Moralia.</note>
                  <note>Translator's dedication signed: Thomas Blondeuille.</note>
                  <note>Title page mutilated in only known copy.</note>
                  <note>Publication date from colophon.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-C⁴; A-D⁴ E⁶ B-K⁴.</note>
                  <note>"The fruytes of foes" and "The porte of reste" have separate divisional titles and register. The latter title is printed on ¹E4r.</note>
                  <note>The first two works are in verse.</note>
                  <note>Identified as STC 20064+ on UMI microfilm.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
                  <note>Letters appearing in brackets in title are supplied in MS.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Ethics --  Greece --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Monica Tsuneishi</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Monica Tsuneishi</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:176515:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:176515:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>¶ Three morall Treatiſes, no leſſe pleaſaunt than neceſſary for all men to reade, wherof the one is called the Learned Prince, the other the Fruites of Foes, the thyrde the Porte of reſt.</p>
            <p>¶ Imprynted at London by Wyllyam Seres, dwellynge at the weſt ende of Poules at the ſigne of the Hedg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hogge.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Cum priuilegio ad imprimendum ſolum.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:176515:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:176515:2"/>
            <head>To the Queenes highnes</head>
            <lg>
               <l>OF all the bookes that euer Plutarke wrote,</l>
               <l>More mete is none, when they haue time &amp; ſpace,</l>
               <l>For Prynces all to rede and well to note:</l>
               <l>Then this, whiche heare I offre to your grace.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>For lyke as he, the good doth iuſtly praiſe,</l>
               <l>The euill their faultes, ſo, plainlye dothe he tell,</l>
               <l>And whilſt he doth conſider both their wayes:</l>
               <l>He ſhewes wherein a Prince ought moſt texcell.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>That is to ſaye in learnynge, wytte, and ſkill,</l>
               <l>To tame affectes, and folowe reaſons lore,</l>
               <l>Whoſe ſteppes doe flethe wayes of froward will:</l>
               <l>And treades the pathes of iuſtice euermore.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And though this Boke, your highnes oft hath redde,</l>
               <l>In Grekyſhe proſe as Plutarke did it wright:</l>
               <l>My rurall muſe, for that, yeat, had no dredde</l>
               <l>In Englyſh verſe, agayne the ſame tendight.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Preſuminge of the fauor whyche ſhe fownde,</l>
               <l>When that ſhe ſange, what fruites of foes might ryſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>And that your grace, gaue eare vnto the ſownde</l>
               <l>Of ſuche rude ryme, as ſhe did then deuyſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Wherfore now harke my liege and ſouraigne Quene</l>
               <l>What Plutarke ſayeth of Prynces good and badde</l>
               <l>Who yf he were alyue to Iudge: I wene,</l>
               <l>Of all the Qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nes in honour to be had,</l>
               <l>Your learninge, and your vertues pondred well,</l>
               <l>He would your grace, ſhould onely beare the bell.</l>
            </lg>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your maieſties moſt humble Subiecte Thomas Blondeuille.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <body>
               <div type="poem">
                  <pb facs="tcp:176515:3"/>
                  <head>The learned Prynce.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>THe <hi>Cyrens</hi> once made greate requeſt,</l>
                     <l>That <hi>Plato</hi> wolde vouchſafe to wright</l>
                     <l>ſuch lawes, as he for the thought beſt,</l>
                     <l>Their ſtate therby, to rule vpright.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>But <hi>Plato</hi> tho, dyd cleane refuſe,</l>
                     <l>So hard a thynge to take in hande,</l>
                     <l>Who knewe, they woulde good lawes abuſe</l>
                     <l>Which had ſuch welth within their lande.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>For nothing is more hard tentreate,</l>
                     <l>More proude, ne worſe to deale wythall,</l>
                     <l>Than is that man, in wealthye ſtate</l>
                     <l>Which thinkes to ſtande, and fearth no fall.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Wherfore it is to harde for ſuche</l>
                     <l>As others rule, and beare the ſwaye,</l>
                     <l>To ſuffer lawes to rule to muche,</l>
                     <l>Leſt than, their power ſhould ſone decaye.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>For reaſon as their Cheffe to take,</l>
                     <l>They doe abhorre: leſt Princely might,</l>
                     <l>They ſhould then forced be to make</l>
                     <l>A ſlaue: to Iuſtice trueth and ryght.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>As men alas which doe not knowe,</l>
                     <l>What <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>eop<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>mp</hi> the Spartan duke</l>
                     <l>Sayd to his wife with voyce full lowe,</l>
                     <l>When ſhe obiected this rebuke.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <pb facs="tcp:176515:3"/>
                     <l>For whereas he dyd fyrſt of all</l>
                     <l>To royall power, <hi>Tribunos</hi> adde:</l>
                     <l>She ſayd thou bryngſt thy Sonne, in thrall,</l>
                     <l>To leaue leſſe powre, then thou haſt hadde.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>No rather yet, then aunſwerde he</l>
                     <l>I ſhall hym leaue ſo muche the more</l>
                     <l>For nowe his powre ſhall ſtronger be</l>
                     <l>Then euer myne was heretofore.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>And thoughe this Prynce hymſelfe depryud</l>
                     <l>Of that whiche he to geue thought good:</l>
                     <l>As thoughe ſmall brookes he had deryud</l>
                     <l>Out of a goulffe, or flowinge floud:</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Remyttynge yet the riguor greate</l>
                     <l>Of royall powre whiche none can beare</l>
                     <l>He dyd auoyde all enuyouſe hate:</l>
                     <l>And leadde his lyfe cleane out of feare.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Yf reaſon gotte by wyſedomes lore</l>
                     <l>Aſſiſt the Prynce: ſhe gardes his health,</l>
                     <l>For ryddynge thill awaye before</l>
                     <l>She leaues the good tencreaſe his wealth.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>But many Kynges that folyſhe are</l>
                     <l>To maſters rude that karue in ſtone</l>
                     <l>And haue no arte, I may compare</l>
                     <l>So lytle diffrence is or none.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <pb facs="tcp:176515:4"/>
                     <l>For they their Images do Iudge</l>
                     <l>Then beſt to make: when that they ſhape</l>
                     <l>them arms &amp; thighes with legges moſt hudge</l>
                     <l>and ougly mouthes full wyde to gape.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Vnprudent kinges euyn ſo I ſaye</l>
                     <l>By frowning lokes, bigge voyce, diſdayne,</l>
                     <l>and keping cloſſe in, all the daye,</l>
                     <l>Great maieſtye do thinke tattaine.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Like Images in outward ſhowe</l>
                     <l>VVhich do pretend ſome goodly one</l>
                     <l>Yeat inwardlye if you wyll knowe</l>
                     <l>they onely are but earth or ſtone.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>In one thinge yeat they diſagree.</l>
                     <l>For Images throughe that their waight</l>
                     <l>and heauy poyſe, faſt ſtabliſht bee:</l>
                     <l>Ne do they moue but ſtande vp ſtraight.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>VVhere fooliſhe kynges vntaught I ſaye</l>
                     <l>For that within they are not ſounde</l>
                     <l>Ne truly waide they ſwarue and ſwaye</l>
                     <l>and oftimes fall vnto the grounde.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>For why vnles to place thou wylt</l>
                     <l>In ſuer wiſe, thy Principall:</l>
                     <l>VVhat euer ſhall theron be buylt:</l>
                     <l>In breffe muſt nedes to ruyne fall.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <pb facs="tcp:176515:4"/>
                     <l>But as the Craftſman ſhould forſee</l>
                     <l>His rule be right and trulye made</l>
                     <l>VVithout all fault before that hee</l>
                     <l>In any woorke do further wade:</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>A Prince likewiſe ought firſt to kno</l>
                     <l>Hymſelfe to rule and rightlye guyde</l>
                     <l>And then to frame his ſubiectes ſo</l>
                     <l>As in good rule they may abyde.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>For whye it is a thinge vnmete</l>
                     <l>A feble man to take in hande</l>
                     <l>to ſet vp others on their fete</l>
                     <l>VVhen he himſelfe can ſcantly ſtande.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Ne likewiſe can it decente be</l>
                     <l>That he ſhould teache whiche hath no ſkill</l>
                     <l>Or order men in eche degre</l>
                     <l>In whom doth raigne diſorder ſtill.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Ne ſhould that man commaunde of right</l>
                     <l>VVhich reaſons rule doth not obaye</l>
                     <l>Though fooles him count of greateſt mighte</l>
                     <l>VVhich ſubiecte is no kynde of waye.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>The kynge of Perce, did all men take</l>
                     <l>To be hys ſlaues and lyue in thrall</l>
                     <l>His wife excepte whom he ſhould make</l>
                     <l>His will tobaye, aboue them all.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <pb facs="tcp:176515:5"/>
                     <l>But ſome perhappes would nowe demaunde</l>
                     <l>
                        <label type="milestone">
                           <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſtion </seg>
                        </label> Who ought to rule a Prynce or Kynge?</l>
                     <l>
                        <label type="milestone">
                           <seg type="milestoneunit">anſwere </seg>
                        </label> The lawe as Quene, who doth commaunde</l>
                     <l>Both Gods and men, as Poets ſynge.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>I meane not that whiche is expreſt,</l>
                     <l>In bokes of paper, wodde, or ſtone,</l>
                     <l>But reaſon graft within his breſt,</l>
                     <l>To guyde his doinges euerychone.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>The Kynge of Pearce was wont to haue</l>
                     <l>A chamberlane whome day by day</l>
                     <l>Wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> mornyng came he ſtrayght charg gaue</l>
                     <l>That he to him theſe wordes ſhoulde ſaye.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Aryſe thou Kynge and ſlepe no more</l>
                     <l>But carefull be to do ryght ſone</l>
                     <l>Suche nedefull thynges as heretofore</l>
                     <l>Meſoromaſdes woulde haue done.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>But Kynges that wyſe and learned are</l>
                     <l>Haue alwayes one within theyr mynde</l>
                     <l>More prompt to tel them of theyr care</l>
                     <l>Then any man that they can fynde,</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Polemon ſayde that Cupyde was</l>
                     <l>A ſeruaunt to the Goddes aboue</l>
                     <l>From place to place with ſpede to paſſe</l>
                     <l>To ſeke what dyd yonge laddes behoue.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <pb facs="tcp:176515:5"/>
                     <l>But one more rightly yet might ſaye</l>
                     <l>Gods miniſters that Prynces bee</l>
                     <l>To take the charge of men alwaye</l>
                     <l>And eke their wealth to well forſee.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>That like as God do lette them haue</l>
                     <l>Thoſe godly giftes which they enioye</l>
                     <l>Some part euyn ſo they ſtill ſhoulde ſaue</l>
                     <l>And wiſelye ought the reſt temploye.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>We ſee the ample heauen howe he,</l>
                     <l>With liquid armes do thearth embrace:</l>
                     <l>Who firſt ſent downe the ſedes whiche ſhe</l>
                     <l>With fruit bringes forth in euery place.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Some growe by raine, and ſome by winde,</l>
                     <l>By glittringe ſtarres ſome noriſſht are</l>
                     <l>And ſome the Moone wyth moyſtures kinde</l>
                     <l>To foſter vppe, hath onelye care.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>And finallye the louelye Sonne</l>
                     <l>Whoſe ſhyning beames adorneth all</l>
                     <l>His frendly courſe doth dayly ronne</l>
                     <l>And ſhewes like loue to great and ſmall.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Theſe godly gyftes yeat can we not</l>
                     <l>Ne rightlye vſe ne well enioy</l>
                     <l>Onles alſo it be oure lot</l>
                     <l>To haue a Prynce <hi>Iuſtice and Ioy.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <pb facs="tcp:176515:6"/>
                     <l>For Iuſtice is of lawe the ende</l>
                     <l>And lawe the Prynces woorke I ſaye</l>
                     <l>The Prynce gods lykenes doth portende</l>
                     <l>Who ouer all muſte beare the ſwaye.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>And neadith not the ſkilfull hande</l>
                     <l>Of Phidias, or Policlette,</l>
                     <l>Of Miron eke or ſuche lyke bande</l>
                     <l>Of thoſe that Carue and colours ſette.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>For he himſelfe by vertue canne</l>
                     <l>Hymſelfe to God moſte lyke deſcrye</l>
                     <l>An Image pleaſinge eurye manne</l>
                     <l>And noble to beholde with eye.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>And lyke as God in heauen aboue</l>
                     <l>The ſhyninge Sonne and Moone doth place</l>
                     <l>In goodlieſt wiſe as beſte behoue</l>
                     <l>To ſhewe his ſhape and lyuelye grace:</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Suche is that Prynce within his lande</l>
                     <l>Whych fearinge God, maintayneth ryght,</l>
                     <l>And reaſons rule doth vnderſtande,</l>
                     <l>VVherin conſiſtes his porte and might.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>And not in Scepter, or in Crowne,</l>
                     <l>In thunder bolt, or glyttringe ſwerde,</l>
                     <l>wherby ſome thinke tobteyne renowne</l>
                     <l>Synce than, they ſhoulde be greatlye ferde.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <pb facs="tcp:176515:6"/>
                     <l>Wheras in dede, for that they ſeme</l>
                     <l>That none to them maye haue acceſſe:</l>
                     <l>They are enuied, and wiſe men denie</l>
                     <l>Suche porte to be greate fooliſhneſſe.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>For God offended is wyth thoſe</l>
                     <l>His thundringe power that imitates:</l>
                     <l>But he delightes in ſuche as choſe</l>
                     <l>In clemency to be hys mates.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>And doth promote them more and more</l>
                     <l>And of his owne benignytye:</l>
                     <l>Doth make them partners of his lore</l>
                     <l>Of iuſtyce, trueth, and equitye.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Whiche thinges in dede are more deuyne</l>
                     <l>Than fyar, light, or phebus courſe,</l>
                     <l>Than ſtarres that riſe or downe declyne</l>
                     <l>Ye endles life it ſelfe, is worſe.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>For why longe life is not the cauſe</l>
                     <l>That God moſte happy counted is</l>
                     <l>But prince of vertue is the clauſe</l>
                     <l>VVheron dependeth all his blis.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>When Alexander ſorye was</l>
                     <l>For Clytos death whome he had ſlayne:</l>
                     <l>Then Anaxarke, ſuche wofull cas</l>
                     <l>To mittigate: to hym gan ſayne.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <pb facs="tcp:176515:7"/>
                     <l>To Clito hapt but Iuſtice tho,</l>
                     <l>Which doth aſſiſte the goddes alway</l>
                     <l>That what ſoeuer Princes do,</l>
                     <l>Should rightfull ſeme without denaye.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Which ſayinge was ne right, ne good,</l>
                     <l>For where the kinge bewaild his cryme:</l>
                     <l>This ſemd to egge him in lyke moode,</l>
                     <l>To do like act an other tyme.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>But if for men it lawfull were</l>
                     <l>Such thinges texamyne as them liſte:</l>
                     <l>Full quickly then, it would appeare</l>
                     <l>That Iuſtice doth not Ioue aſſiſte.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>For Iuſtyce euyn it ſelfe to be,</l>
                     <l>Almightye Ioue we ought to take:</l>
                     <l>A lawe of moſt antiquitye</l>
                     <l>Which neuer dyd the trueth forſake.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>The old men alſo plainlye ſaye</l>
                     <l>It paſſeth Ioue his poure and might</l>
                     <l>When ladye Iuſtice is awaye:</l>
                     <l>A kyngdome for to rule vpright.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Who as Heſyode hath vs tought</l>
                     <l>A virgyn is immaculate,</l>
                     <l>A ſhamefaſt maide, which neuer wrought</l>
                     <l>But modeſtlye wyth eurye ſtate.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <pb facs="tcp:176515:7"/>
                     <l>And hereof kinges ſurnamed are</l>
                     <l>Right reuerent, and dredefull aye:</l>
                     <l>For thoſe in whome doth dwell leaſt feare,</l>
                     <l>Ought to be feared moſte I ſaye.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>But it behoues muche more a kynge</l>
                     <l>To feare to do, then ſuffer ille,</l>
                     <l>For of the one the other ſprynge,</l>
                     <l>So do ſo haue is Iuſtice wille.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>This Princely feare a Prynce lykewyſe</l>
                     <l>Should alwayes haue: Vnwares that leſt</l>
                     <l>To hym, for lacke of carefull eyes:</l>
                     <l>With wronges his ſubiectes be oppreſt.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>For ſo the dogges that watche the folde</l>
                     <l>When they the cruell wolfe do heare:</l>
                     <l>Not for themſelues which are full bolde,</l>
                     <l>But for their charge haue onely feare.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Epamynond the Theban knight</l>
                     <l>His ſubiectes tendinge feaſtes and playe</l>
                     <l>Would all alone both day and night</l>
                     <l>Kepe watche and warde and oftymes ſaye.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>That he dyd aye lyue ſoberlye</l>
                     <l>And watchfull was to that intente</l>
                     <l>That others myght more quyetlye</l>
                     <l>Be dronke, and ſlepe, as they were bente.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <pb facs="tcp:176515:8"/>
                     <l>VVhen Cezar hadde at vtique towne,</l>
                     <l>to Cato yeuen the ouerthro:</l>
                     <l>the reſte vnſlayne, then Cato downe</l>
                     <l>Did call: vnto the ſea to go.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>And hauinge ſene them ſafelye ſhipte</l>
                     <l>and wyſht them well to paſſe the ſea:</l>
                     <l>as one with fewer cares beclipte,</l>
                     <l>Retourned home himſelfe to ſlea.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>By which enſample Cato heare,</l>
                     <l>Doth teache all Princes that be wiſe,</l>
                     <l>Of what, they ſhould haue greateſt feare,</l>
                     <l>And what againe, they ſhould deſpiſe.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>But on the other part beholde</l>
                     <l>Clearchus cruell kinge of Ponte,</l>
                     <l>Howe lyke a Serpente layde in folde</l>
                     <l>In cheſt cloſſe ſhut to ſlepe was wonte.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Full lyke Tariſtodeme therefore</l>
                     <l>VVho in his dyninge chamber hadde</l>
                     <l>A cloſette with a fallynge dore</l>
                     <l>And eke with beddynge fynelye cladde.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>VVherin his concupyne and he</l>
                     <l>VVere wont all nyght to take their reſt,</l>
                     <l>And to thintente that none ſhould ſe</l>
                     <l>Ne come to vexe them in their neſt:</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <pb facs="tcp:176515:8"/>
                     <l>The mother of the damſell ſhould</l>
                     <l>The ſtayer cleane from thence remoue</l>
                     <l>And ſet it, theare againſt they would</l>
                     <l>come downe next mornynge from aboue.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Howe much thynke you would this man flee</l>
                     <l>A Palays, Courte, or Feaſtynge place</l>
                     <l>VVhich of hys chamber as you ſee</l>
                     <l>A priſon made to kepe his grace.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Thus trew kynges haue no feare in dede</l>
                     <l>But aye for thoſe, on whom they raigne:</l>
                     <l>But Tyrantes for theym ſelues haue drede</l>
                     <l>Leſt for their vice they ſhoulde be ſlaine.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>The greater powre, the greater feare,</l>
                     <l>The more to rule, that they obtayne:</l>
                     <l>The more as foes to them appeare,</l>
                     <l>VVherby they growe in more diſdayne.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>VVyth matter apt all ſhapes to take</l>
                     <l>And ſubiect aye to ſondry chaunge</l>
                     <l>Of god ſome would a mixture make</l>
                     <l>and hyde hym theare which is full ſtraunge.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>But Plato ſayith God dwelles aboue</l>
                     <l>And there faſt fixt in holy ſawes:</l>
                     <l>From trueth he neuer doth remoue</l>
                     <l>Ne ſwarues from natures ſtedfaſt lawes.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <pb facs="tcp:176515:9"/>
                     <l>And as in heauen lyke to a glaſſe</l>
                     <l>The ſonne his ſhape doth repreſente:</l>
                     <l>In earth, the light of Iuſtyce was</l>
                     <l>By hym ordeynd: for lyke intente.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>VVhich ſhape all wyſe and happy men</l>
                     <l>To counterfete employe theyr payne</l>
                     <l>Full buſuly wyth wyſdomes pen</l>
                     <l>The chefeſte blis therby tattaine.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>But nothing can this habit brede</l>
                     <l>In vs ſo ſone, as reaſons lore</l>
                     <l>Got out of wyſdoms ſchole in dede:</l>
                     <l>To guyde our doynges euer more</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>VVhen Alexander hadde well tryde</l>
                     <l>The prompt wytte of Diogenes</l>
                     <l>And ſene his ſtoutnes great beſyde:</l>
                     <l>He marueyled, and ſayde, doutles:</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>If I not Alexander were,</l>
                     <l>I woulde become diogenes,</l>
                     <l>As one that vertue woulde fayne leare:</l>
                     <l>But princely powre dyd hym oppreſſe.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>VVhich would not graunt him time tapply:</l>
                     <l>The thinge ſo muche eſtemed aye</l>
                     <l>For lacke whereof he did enuy?</l>
                     <l>The Cinickes ſcrippe, and pore araye.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <pb facs="tcp:176515:9"/>
                     <l>VVherewith he ſawe the Cinicke made</l>
                     <l>At all aſſayes more ſtronge and ſtouts</l>
                     <l>Than he hymſelfe when to inuade</l>
                     <l>Of horſe and men had greateſt route.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Thus in deſiar and good will</l>
                     <l>Diogenes the kinge might be</l>
                     <l>And yeat in dede remayning ſtill</l>
                     <l>In princelye ſtate and highe degre.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Yea, he, more nede had in this cas</l>
                     <l>To be diogenes aryght:</l>
                     <l>In that he Alexander was</l>
                     <l>An emprour great of powre and might.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Who hadde in fortunes ſeas to ſtryue</l>
                     <l>With cruell ſtormes and rockes beſyde</l>
                     <l>Wheron his ſhippe might eaſlye dryue</l>
                     <l>Onles he had the better guyde.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>For priuate men of lowe degre</l>
                     <l>That others can offende no waye</l>
                     <l>Thoughe they taffectes oft ſubiect be</l>
                     <l>Their greues yeat are but dreams I ſaye.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>But whereas powre is ioynd vnto</l>
                     <l>Euill ordred life, thear thinke it true</l>
                     <l>That ſuch affectes will cauſe alſo</l>
                     <l>Great grefe in dede for to enſewe.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <pb facs="tcp:176515:10"/>
                     <l>The chefeſt fruit that Dioniſe</l>
                     <l>Dyd of his empyre take: it was,</l>
                     <l>(He ſayde) what he dyd than deuiſe,</l>
                     <l>With ſpede to haue it brought to paſſe.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>A thyng moſt peryllouſe therfore</l>
                     <l>It is, vndecent thynges to wyll:</l>
                     <l>When he that wylleth, euermore</l>
                     <l>Hath powre, the ſame for to fulfyll.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>For powre doth malice quickly moue,</l>
                     <l>With euyll affectes the mynd to ſtreke</l>
                     <l>As enuy, wrath, aduowtry, loue,</l>
                     <l>Mens goodes alſo, and lyues to ſeke.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>And then the worde nys ſoner ſayde,</l>
                     <l>But wo to hym that is ſuſpect</l>
                     <l>Toffende in that to hym is layde,</l>
                     <l>For ſentence there, muſt take effect.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Of nature, ſuch as ſearchers be:</l>
                     <l>Do hold that after thunder clapp</l>
                     <l>The lyghtnyng coms, yeat do we ſe</l>
                     <l>The ſame before we heare the rapp.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>The bludd lykewyſe before the wound</l>
                     <l>To vs moſt commonly appeares:</l>
                     <l>For ſight doth mete the light; wheare ſound</l>
                     <l>Is fayne to come euin to our eares.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <pb facs="tcp:176515:10"/>
                     <l>In kyngdoms ſo, ſome men we fynde</l>
                     <l>Taue ſuffred eare, thaccuſed were</l>
                     <l>And ſentence yeuen to wrath inclynde</l>
                     <l>Before due profe of cryme appeare.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>For wrath nought hable is twithſtand</l>
                     <l>The powre of malice when ſhe liſt,</l>
                     <l>As is the anker firt in ſande</l>
                     <l>Which can the cruell ſea reſiſt.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Onles that reaſon with her wayght</l>
                     <l>Preſſe downe ſuch powre, and kynges abyde</l>
                     <l>To marke the ſonne, in greateſt hayght</l>
                     <l>Howe he hymſelfe doth wyſly guyde.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>For when he mownted is aloft</l>
                     <l>To Cancers ryng, he ſemes to ſtay,</l>
                     <l>In that he goeth ſo fayre and ſoft</l>
                     <l>Wherby he doth aſſure his way.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>But this by dayly profe we knowe</l>
                     <l>Where powre and malyce do abyde:</l>
                     <l>There, malyce nedes, her ſelfe muſt ſhowe,</l>
                     <l>And can her face no long tyme hyde.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>If thoſe that haue the fallyng yll</l>
                     <l>At any tyme take colde I ſay,</l>
                     <l>They can not ſtand but ſtagger ſtyll</l>
                     <l>Which playnely doth theyr grefe bewray.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:176515:12"/>
                  <l>But only wyſſhe and dayly craue</l>
                  <l>Of god to graunt, that ouer vs</l>
                  <l>Long tyme of raigne her bygones haue</l>
                  <l>Which is ſo good and gracious.</l>
                  <trailer>Finis.</trailer>
                  <pb facs="tcp:176515:12"/>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:176515:11"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:176515:11"/>
                  <p>¶ The fruytes of Foes. Newly corrected and cleanſed of manye faultes eſcaped in the former printing.</p>
                  <p>Anno domini. M.D.LXI.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Cum priuilegio ad imprimendum ſolum.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="poem">
                  <pb facs="tcp:176515:13"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:176515:13"/>
                  <head>¶ Roger Aſcham Secretory to the Queenes maieſtie, for the latin tongue, in praiſe of the booke.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>F Engliſh bokes, as I could find,</l>
                     <l>I haue peruſed many one:</l>
                     <l>Yet ſo wel done vnto my mind,</l>
                     <l>As this is, yet haue I fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d none</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>The woordes of matter here doe riſe,</l>
                     <l>So fitly and ſo naturally,</l>
                     <l>As heart can wiſhe or witte deuiſe</l>
                     <l>In my conceit and fantaſie.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>The woordes well choſen and well ſette,</l>
                     <l>Doe bryng ſuche light vnto the ſenſe:</l>
                     <l>As if I lackt I woulde not lette,</l>
                     <l>To bye this booke for forty penſe.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="dedication">
                  <pb facs="tcp:176515:14"/>
                  <head>To the Queenes highnes</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>SVch Newyeres giftes as moſt me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> do prepare</l>
                     <l>To geue your grace, it paſſeth far my powre.</l>
                     <l>For golde ne pearle, ne ſuch lyke coſtly ware,</l>
                     <l>Can I poſſeſſe: ſith fortune ſtyll doth lowre.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>As ſhe on me hath hereto euer done,</l>
                     <l>Which had me brought at length to great diſtreſſe</l>
                     <l>But that the hope, which in your grace alone</l>
                     <l>I alwayes fixt: my griefes did oft redreſſe.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Which hope I ſay, euen now doth make me bolde</l>
                     <l>Your royall ſtate, with this ſo ſmall a queyre</l>
                     <l>For to preſent: yea more, that hope me tolde,</l>
                     <l>From this day forth, I ſhould no more diſpeire.</l>
                     <l>For loe, (ſaith ſhe) the golden worlde at hande,</l>
                     <l>And Iuſtice raignes again within this lande.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Your maieſties moſt humble ſeruant. Thomas Blundeuille.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="poem">
                  <pb facs="tcp:176515:14"/>
                  <head>The fruites of Foes.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>I Plutarks lore of mortal foes,</l>
                     <l>Learne ye y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> liſt ſome fruit to take,</l>
                     <l>For fruits inough, he doth diſclees</l>
                     <l>Wherof I wil, you partners make</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>In olde time paſt, me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> only ſought,</l>
                     <l>The hurtfull beaſtes, their foes to kyll,</l>
                     <l>Of other ſpoyle, they nothyng thought,</l>
                     <l>But ſo to ſaue themſelues from ill.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>But others came then afterwarde,</l>
                     <l>Whoſe ſleight was ſuch, thoſe beaſtes to ſlay:</l>
                     <l>As they thereto had ſmall regarde,</l>
                     <l>Except they myght obtaine ſome pray.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Their fleſhe to eate, they vſde therfore,</l>
                     <l>And with their wolle, themſelues to cladde,</l>
                     <l>Their milke and galle they kept in ſtore:</l>
                     <l>To heale ſuche griefes, as ſicke men hadde.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>And of their hydes, they harnes made,</l>
                     <l>Themſelues to arme, on euery ſyde:</l>
                     <l>That they might aye in ſafety wade</l>
                     <l>Againſt all force, that might betyde.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Loe thus by foes, no hurt to take,</l>
                     <l>It did not them at all ſuffiſe,</l>
                     <l>Except they might ſuch great gaine make:</l>
                     <l>As they themſelues could beſt deuiſe.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <pb facs="tcp:176515:15"/>
                     <l>If thou therfore, without ſome hate,</l>
                     <l>Here cannot liue in quiet reſt:</l>
                     <l>Inuent ſome way of ſuch debate,</l>
                     <l>To leaue the worſt, and take the beſt.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>No tylman can by arte deuiſe,</l>
                     <l>Eche tree to ſpoyle, of nature wilde:</l>
                     <l>Nor huntſman eke, be he right wiſe,</l>
                     <l>Can tame eche beaſt, that roons in fyelde.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Wherfore they haue right wiſely founde,</l>
                     <l>The meane tapply ſuch beaſt and tree,</l>
                     <l>To other vſe, which doth redounde,</l>
                     <l>Vnto their great commoditee.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>The water of the ſea, we ſee,</l>
                     <l>Is ſalte, and hath vpleaſante taſte:</l>
                     <l>Yet cheifly thence, I ſay haue wee,</l>
                     <l>The fiſhe, our foode, which we do waſte.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Yea, more then that, thinges of great price,</l>
                     <l>The ſhipps by ſea to vs do brynge,</l>
                     <l>Both pleaſant ſilke, and holſome ſpice,</l>
                     <l>And many other nedefull thinge.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>The brightnes of the flaminge fire,</l>
                     <l>Appearing in the Satirs ſight:</l>
                     <l>Straight waies, ſo kindled his deſire.</l>
                     <l>That it timbrace, he toke delight.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <pb facs="tcp:176515:15"/>
                     <l>Prometheus, then loude can crie,</l>
                     <l>Beware he ſaide imbrace none ſuche,</l>
                     <l>For that it hath the propertie:</l>
                     <l>To burne all thoſe, that doth it tuche.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>It was not made to colle, and kiſſe,</l>
                     <l>But heate, and light, alwaies to yelde:</l>
                     <l>The very meane alſo it is:</l>
                     <l>Whereby craftes men, their artes doe welde.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Hereby therfore, we may perceiue,</l>
                     <l>That of our foe right perilous,</l>
                     <l>In this our lyfe we may receiue,</l>
                     <l>Suche fruites as be commodious.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>For though ſome thynges be very ill,</l>
                     <l>To thoſe, to whom they appertaine,</l>
                     <l>Yet vſde they may be, with ſuche ſkyll:</l>
                     <l>As loſſe ſhall eaſily turne to gaine.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>As loe for proofe, ſome ſickly corſe</l>
                     <l>For eaſementes ſake, ſekes quiet reſt.</l>
                     <l>VVhere ſome againe, to win their force,</l>
                     <l>To trauell oft, do thinke it beſt.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Diogenes and Crates chaunce,</l>
                     <l>Do well declare, how baniſhmentes</l>
                     <l>And loſſe of goodes, doe ſome auaunce</l>
                     <l>To knowledge great, which them contentes.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <pb facs="tcp:176515:16"/>
                     <l>VVhen Zeno heard, that tempeſtes gret,</l>
                     <l>In raginge ſea, his ſhip had loſt:</l>
                     <l>He mourned not ne yet did fret,</l>
                     <l>But made as though it lytle coſt</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>And thus gan ſay, to fortune tho,</l>
                     <l>Howe dearely doeſt thou me entreate:</l>
                     <l>Me thus to force, againe to go,</l>
                     <l>In wyſedoms ſchoole, to fynde a ſeate.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Some beaſtes we ſee, ſuch ſtomakes haue</l>
                     <l>As ſerpentes cauſe full ſoone diſgeaſt,</l>
                     <l>Both woode and ſtone, they alſo craue</l>
                     <l>Suche kynde of foode, them hurteth leaſt.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>But ſome againe, ſo deinty bene</l>
                     <l>That they oft loth, the fineſt bredde,</l>
                     <l>And pureſt wine, that can be ſene:</l>
                     <l>VVherwith they myght be alwayes fedde.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Euen ſo fares fooles, that frendſhip ioyes,</l>
                     <l>Do aye deſtroye, but to the wyſe:</l>
                     <l>Of hatefull ſtrife and ſpightfull toyes,</l>
                     <l>Great wealth, and gaine, dothe oft aryſe.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>VVherefore, me thinkes, where in thy foe</l>
                     <l>Doth ſeme to geue the greateſt grief:</l>
                     <l>Thou mayſt thereof, receiue alſo</l>
                     <l>Muche greater gayne to thy reliefe.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <pb facs="tcp:176515:16"/>
                     <l>And if thou aſke, how that may be,</l>
                     <l>I ſaye to thee, conſider then,</l>
                     <l>What care he hath, thy workes to ſe,</l>
                     <l>With whom, to whom, what, where, &amp; when.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>With Linx his eyes, he doth beholde,</l>
                     <l>Thy lyfe, thy frende, and ſeruaunte aye,</l>
                     <l>Thy dedes, and thoughtes right manifolde,</l>
                     <l>Thy name to harme, if that he maye.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Thys profyt eke, by foes we haue</l>
                     <l>Our frendes oft tymes, we doe not minde,</l>
                     <l>They may be ſick, and layde in graue,</l>
                     <l>Vnwares to vs, lyke men vnkinde.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>But of oure foe, both day and night</l>
                     <l>We thinke and dreame, ſuch is our choyſe,</l>
                     <l>His grief, or bane, to haue in ſight:</l>
                     <l>Which onely doth, our mindes reioyce.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>If thou be ſick, or much in det,</l>
                     <l>Falne out with wife, with mayde, or man,</l>
                     <l>Yea, no miſhap can thee beſet:</l>
                     <l>But, it, thy foes, eft ſone knowe can.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Lyke rauening birdes, that putryd fleſhe,</l>
                     <l>And not the ſounde, far of can ſmell,</l>
                     <l>So they thy illes, to ſpye be freſhe,</l>
                     <l>And all thy griefes, with eye full fell.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <pb facs="tcp:176515:17"/>
                     <l>What greater gaine may be than this,</l>
                     <l>Hereby to learne, in ſuche a ſort</l>
                     <l>Our life to leade, as none there is:</l>
                     <l>That ill therof may once report.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>For as ſicke men that wary be,</l>
                     <l>In meates and drinkes, that may offende:</l>
                     <l>In wordes and dedes, euen ſo doe we</l>
                     <l>Take hede that they the beſt pretende.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Wherby we come in ſchole to dwell,</l>
                     <l>Of cuſtomes good, and excellent,</l>
                     <l>For reaſon rules thaffections fell:</l>
                     <l>Wherto our myndes be alwales bent.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Yea, through long time, and exercyſe,</l>
                     <l>It bredes in vs, ſuch ſtedfaſtnes:</l>
                     <l>That learne we can none other guiſe,</l>
                     <l>But aye to liue in holynes.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>The townes that long haue bene beſet,</l>
                     <l>With enmies ſtout on euery ſide:</l>
                     <l>Haue derely learnde, by loſſes gret,</l>
                     <l>To kepe good watche in euery ride.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>And eke their lawes and ordinaunce,</l>
                     <l>To execute with iuſtice aye</l>
                     <l>The humble ſort for to aduaunce:</l>
                     <l>The proude to chaſt, that nyll obay.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <pb facs="tcp:176515:17"/>
                     <l>Euen ſo fare thoſe that forced bee,</l>
                     <l>Through ſpightfull foes, both negligence,</l>
                     <l>And ſlouthfulnes alwaies to flee</l>
                     <l>Whereby they liue without offence.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>For cuſtome ſhall them bring with ſpede,</l>
                     <l>To ſuche a trade of doyng well,</l>
                     <l>That if they goe as reaſon lede:</l>
                     <l>In errour none, they can long dwell.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>VVhen minſtrels of one ſute and bande</l>
                     <l>In open place doe muſicke make:</l>
                     <l>VVithout all feare, and care they ſtande,</l>
                     <l>And to their play, no hede doe take.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>But when their ſkyll, they doe compare</l>
                     <l>VVith ſtraungers, that profeſſe lyke art:</l>
                     <l>They ſharpe their wittes, and haue great care,</l>
                     <l>That euery one may doe his part.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Of inſtrumentes, and eke of ſtringes,</l>
                     <l>They ſeke where they maye haue beſt choyce,</l>
                     <l>And oft doe proue, how with ſuche thinges</l>
                     <l>May beſt agree, both hande and voice.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Euen ſo it fares with him, whoſe lyfe</l>
                     <l>And honour bothe, muche ſpighted is</l>
                     <l>By thoſe that ſekes, with hatefull ſtrife</l>
                     <l>Hys thinges to blame that be amis.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <pb facs="tcp:176515:18"/>
                     <l>Full ware is he in buſines,</l>
                     <l>And eke foreſees therof the ende,</l>
                     <l>For when we erre: malitiouſnes</l>
                     <l>Regardes the foe, more than the frende.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>When Carthage was all torne and rent,</l>
                     <l>And Greece ſubdude, the Romaines thought</l>
                     <l>Themſelues full ſafe, their foes thus ſhent,</l>
                     <l>They were all gladde, and feared nought.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>But Scipio did then repreue,</l>
                     <l>In perill moſt be we (quoth he)</l>
                     <l>When no foe is, that may vs greue,</l>
                     <l>Whoſe feare ſhould make vs ſlouth to fle,</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>One aſked once Diogenes</l>
                     <l>How he might beſt reuenged bee</l>
                     <l>Of all his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>oes, both more and les,</l>
                     <l>That from all care he mighte be free.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Diogenes right wiſely tho</l>
                     <l>To him gan ſaye, no dent of knife</l>
                     <l>Can greue ſo much thy cruell fo:</l>
                     <l>As for to ſee thy perfit lyfe.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>What grudge, what griefe, the common ſort</l>
                     <l>Conceiues to ſee, the go odly horſe</l>
                     <l>And courſing dogges, which but for ſport,</l>
                     <l>To kepe: their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>es do litle force.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <pb facs="tcp:176515:18"/>
                     <l>What playntes, what ſighthes, &amp; dolfull ſownds</l>
                     <l>Their ſpightfull breaſtes to heauen do yelde,</l>
                     <l>To ſee their pleaſant garden growndes,</l>
                     <l>Or ſtore of corne to growe in fielde.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>How much more then, would they lament,</l>
                     <l>To ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e their foe to be full iuſte?</l>
                     <l>In worde and dede, to vertue bent,</l>
                     <l>Of ſober life, and free from luſt.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>And eke to budde out of his breſt,</l>
                     <l>That fraighted is, with holynes</l>
                     <l>Such domes, and councels, as are beſt,</l>
                     <l>To eaſe eche heart in heauynes.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>The tonges of them, that conquerde bee,</l>
                     <l>Are bounde from ſpeache, ſaith Pindarus:</l>
                     <l>And yet theſe wordes, as you ſhall ſee,</l>
                     <l>To all be not approbrious.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>But only do ſuche men reproue,</l>
                     <l>As nedes muſt yelde, vnto their foes,</l>
                     <l>In all thoſe vertues, that behoue,</l>
                     <l>A perfit man for to diſcloſe.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>For ſuche thinges faith Dimoſthenes</l>
                     <l>Do binde the tonge in torment aye,</l>
                     <l>And ſtoppes the mouth of them doutles</l>
                     <l>That thinkes more ill, then they dare ſaye.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <pb facs="tcp:176515:19"/>
                     <l>Enforce to ſhewe thy ſelfe therfore,</l>
                     <l>Sith in thy power it doth conſiſt:</l>
                     <l>Thy lyfe to guide by vertues lore,</l>
                     <l>Their wicked tonges for to reſiſt.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>And when thou wouldſt faine put thy foe,</l>
                     <l>In great diſpaire, take not the waye</l>
                     <l>By haynous wordes, as others doe,</l>
                     <l>His name to perſecute I ſaye.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Ne beaſtly man, ne filthy foole</l>
                     <l>Doe thou hym call, but rather ſeke,</l>
                     <l>In ſuche a ſort thy ſelfe to ſchoole,</l>
                     <l>That none thy doynges maye miſleke.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Be true thy ſelfe, in woorde and dede</l>
                     <l>Be modeſt ſtyll, and chaſt alſo</l>
                     <l>Shewe curteſy in tyme of nede</l>
                     <l>To ſuche as haue with thee to do.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>And if it ſhoulde ſo come to paſſe,</l>
                     <l>That nedes, thy foe thou muſt reproue</l>
                     <l>For any fault: yet in that caſe,</l>
                     <l>See firſt thy ſelfe thou doe wel proue.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Examine eke with diligence,</l>
                     <l>Thine inward partes if they be free,</l>
                     <l>From all ſuche vire and negligence:</l>
                     <l>as in thy foe, thou ſemſte to ſee.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <pb facs="tcp:176515:19"/>
                     <l>For els perhaps thou maiſt geue cauſe,</l>
                     <l>To ſome ill tonge, that ſtandes thee by:</l>
                     <l>With voyce full ſoft, to ſaye this clauſe,</l>
                     <l>Recited in a Tragedie.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Beholde I ſaye this fooliſhe man,</l>
                     <l>That takes in hande the woundes to cure</l>
                     <l>Of other men: and yet nought can</l>
                     <l>His owne redreſſe, I you aſſure.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>But if he call thee ignoraunt,</l>
                     <l>Learne wiſedome then by induſtrie</l>
                     <l>Thy faynty heart, if he doe taunt</l>
                     <l>Let ſtoutnes ſhew thou wilt not flie.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>If he thee checke for lecherie,</l>
                     <l>Auoide eche ſparke of filthines,</l>
                     <l>Out of thy breaſt full ſpedilie,</l>
                     <l>and learne to liue in holines.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>More foule or grieuous nothing is</l>
                     <l>Then for a man ſuche faultes to checke</l>
                     <l>As all the ſhame therof ywis</l>
                     <l>Againe ſhall turne vpon his necke.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>For as rebounde of glittering light,</l>
                     <l>The feble ſight doth moſte offende:</l>
                     <l>Euen ſo moſt grieuous is the ſpight,</l>
                     <l>Which trueth beates back, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whence it wende.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <pb facs="tcp:176515:20"/>
                     <l>The miſtie cloudes vnto the winde,</l>
                     <l>that blowes Northeaſt, doe aye reſort,</l>
                     <l>The wicked life euen ſo we fynde</l>
                     <l>To her doth drawe all ill report.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>If any man in Platoes ſight</l>
                     <l>Had vilye done, ſtraight thence would he,</l>
                     <l>And ſoftly ſay, may any wight,</l>
                     <l>Such one as he, me force to be?</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>But when thou haſte with wordes of ire</l>
                     <l>Thy foe yprict, for his offence:</l>
                     <l>Beholde thy ſelf, and eke deſire</l>
                     <l>Thy lyfe tamende, with diligence.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Of ſpightfull wordes ſo ſhalt thou drawe</l>
                     <l>Muche fruite, to thy greate welth and gaine</l>
                     <l>Though ſome it thinke, ne right ne lawe,</l>
                     <l>To vſe ſuch wordes, of great diſdayne.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>The common ſort, do laughe, and ſmyle,</l>
                     <l>VVhen any balde or crooked man,</l>
                     <l>Do others taunt, and oft reuyle,</l>
                     <l>For ſuch defectes, as themſelues han.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>VVhat greater ſcorne, then woulde it bee,</l>
                     <l>If thou ſuche faultes ſhouldſt reprehende:</l>
                     <l>As one with worſe, might aunſwer thee</l>
                     <l>VVhich thou in no wyſe couldſt defende.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <pb facs="tcp:176515:20"/>
                     <l>As once, did Leo Bizantine,</l>
                     <l>When one that had a crooked backe,</l>
                     <l>Hym caſt in teeth his bleared eyne</l>
                     <l>alas (quoth he) this is no lacke.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>A humaine thing this is, I ſay,</l>
                     <l>But why alas canſt not eſpye:</l>
                     <l>Howe on thy backe thou beareſt alway,</l>
                     <l>That goddeſſe fell, dame Nemeſye?<note place="margin">Nemeſis Godd<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ſſe r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>uenge.</note>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Aduouterer, ſee none thou call</l>
                     <l>Whilſt fouler luſt in thee dothe raigne:</l>
                     <l>Ne yet reproue the prodigall,</l>
                     <l>If auarice thy lyfe dothe ſtaine.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Alemeon when he did reuile,</l>
                     <l>Adraſtus, king: of kin thou art</l>
                     <l>(Quoth he) vnto that woman vile:</l>
                     <l>Whiche carft with knife, her huſbandes hart.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Adraſtus then, him aunſwerd loe,</l>
                     <l>With that whiche did him touche at quicke</l>
                     <l>Suche beaſtly wrathe in thee did floe</l>
                     <l>Thy dame to ſlea ere ſhe were ſicke.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>When Dyoniſe did Craſſus ſkorne,</l>
                     <l>For that he wailde, his Lampreys cas,</l>
                     <l>By crewell death, then all forlorne,</l>
                     <l>Whiche in his ponde, long foſtred was.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <pb facs="tcp:176515:21"/>
                     <l>Then Craſſus ſaid, rebuke not mee</l>
                     <l>Sith that from thee no teares did fall</l>
                     <l>The death to ſee, of thy wiues three</l>
                     <l>Nor felſt no grief, therby at all.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>VVho ſo delightes to checke or taunt,</l>
                     <l>No rybalde, knaue, or foole muſt bee:</l>
                     <l>VVith bragging woordes, hymſelf to vaunt,</l>
                     <l>But rather ſhould from vyce be free.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>VVherfore, none ſemes more bound tobay,</l>
                     <l>Apollos woorde (thine own ſelf know:)</l>
                     <l>Then thoſe that are moſt prompt alway</l>
                     <l>To rayle, to ieſt, to mocke, and mowe.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>For hap, it may, ſaith Sophocles,</l>
                     <l>That whilſt they taunt, as them likes beſt:</l>
                     <l>To them again, is ſaid doubtles:</l>
                     <l>That whiche to heare, they couet leſt.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>In tauntyng thus our foes, we finde</l>
                     <l>No litle fruit, but more we gaine,</l>
                     <l>VVhen they likewiſe, with wordes vnkinde,</l>
                     <l>Our faultes to taunt, do not refraine.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Anthiſtines ſaid well therfore,</l>
                     <l>That lyfe, in ſafety to encloes</l>
                     <l>Man ought to haue alwaies in ſtore:</l>
                     <l>Right perfit frendes, or bitter foes.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <pb facs="tcp:176515:21"/>
                     <l>For faithfull frendes wyll vs reforme</l>
                     <l>VVhen that we erre: our foes againe</l>
                     <l>VVyll ſo muche rayle, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>d out of forme,</l>
                     <l>That nedes from vyce, we muſt abſtaine.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>But ſyth that now true frendſhip is</l>
                     <l>Of free ſpeche ſpoylde, and flattry bent</l>
                     <l>To chatte, and prate of thynges amyſſe</l>
                     <l>Good counſels eke muſt nedes all ſtent.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>And therefore nothing now remaines</l>
                     <l>For vs to doe: but to abide,</l>
                     <l>The trueth to heare, to our great paynes,</l>
                     <l>By ſpightfull foes, that nought wyll hyde.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>When Telephus his feſtred wounde</l>
                     <l>Could no wiſe heale: with thenmies ſpeare</l>
                     <l>VVhich firſt him hurt louelyfe, him bound,</l>
                     <l>To launce theſame without all feare.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Euen ſo muſt they of force agree</l>
                     <l>To byde reprofe of ſpightful foes:</l>
                     <l>VVhere wanteth frendes their faultes to ſee,</l>
                     <l>And frankly wyll theſame diſcloſe.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Nor in this caſe, we ſhould behold</l>
                     <l>Our foes intent, when they ſo rayle,</l>
                     <l>But if ſuch thinges as they haue tolde,</l>
                     <l>Be true in vs, or els doe fayle.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <pb facs="tcp:176515:22"/>
                     <l>Prothemeus of Theſſalie</l>
                     <l>A grieuous ſore had in his breaſt:</l>
                     <l>Whiche one that was his enemie,</l>
                     <l>Did cure by chaunce againſte his heaſt.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>For when he thought to haue him ſlain,</l>
                     <l>By dent of ſword he brake the ſore,</l>
                     <l>Which feſtred was to his great pain,</l>
                     <l>And ſo hym helde for euermore.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Euen ſo full oft it comes to paſſe,</l>
                     <l>That wordes yſpoke for ill intent,</l>
                     <l>Do greatly helpe, ſome one that was</l>
                     <l>His fault tamend: ful negligent.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>But moſt men when they are reuilde</l>
                     <l>Haue no regarde, if with ſuch vice,</l>
                     <l>As is them tolde, they be defilde:</l>
                     <l>But ſekes reuenge, by lyke aduice.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>VVhere reaſon would that ſuche as are</l>
                     <l>By foes rebukte, for their offence:</l>
                     <l>Should afterward thereof beware,</l>
                     <l>And ſeke redreſſe with diligence.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Yea, more then that, without deſart,</l>
                     <l>Though they vs check, for any thing:</l>
                     <l>To ſeke yet then, it is our part,</l>
                     <l>The cauſe wherof the ſame did ſpring.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <pb facs="tcp:176515:22"/>
                     <l>And eke to feare leſt eare we thought,</l>
                     <l>VVe haue the ſame or ſuch lyke don</l>
                     <l>For one ſuſpect, hath many brought</l>
                     <l>To ſhame, and great deriſion.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>As thargiue kyng ſir Lacydes,</l>
                     <l>Becauſe he was ſo nice of gate</l>
                     <l>And eke his heere would finely dreſſe</l>
                     <l>VVith finger aye, was poynted ate.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>And cald a man effeminat,</l>
                     <l>The lyke to Pompey dyd befall,</l>
                     <l>For that he vſde his hedde to ſcrat:</l>
                     <l>VVhen he no hurt, dyd thinke at all.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>For none did more then he, deſpyſe</l>
                     <l>Such wanton luſt and tendernes,</l>
                     <l>VVho aye was bent to enterpriſe:</l>
                     <l>Thynges great of weight and hardines.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>So Craſſus eke to tell you plaine,</l>
                     <l>Suſpected was through ſuche lyke tale,</l>
                     <l>For that he did as ſome men fayne,</l>
                     <l>Frequent full oft, a maide veſtale.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>And yet in dede his connyng nas,</l>
                     <l>For any hurt or ill intent:</l>
                     <l>But cer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ain land to hye, in cas,</l>
                     <l>He could obtayne her free concent,</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <pb facs="tcp:176515:23"/>
                     <l>Poſthumia through mirth and playe,</l>
                     <l>And hauntyng oft without reſpect</l>
                     <l>Mens company, her name I ſaye</l>
                     <l>VVith infamy dyd ſore infect.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>For whiche ſhe cited was tappere,</l>
                     <l>As one that had in lecherie:</l>
                     <l>Abuſde her ſelfe, with kinſfolkes nere:</l>
                     <l>And yet ſhe dyd no villany.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>VVhom though that Spurius, whiche hight</l>
                     <l>Manutius, then biſhop hye,</l>
                     <l>Of that ill fame, did cleane acquight,</l>
                     <l>He warnde her yet thus fatherly.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Poſthumia, ſith that thou haſte,</l>
                     <l>In holy workes, thy lyfe aye ledde,</l>
                     <l>Leſt wanton talke, thy name may waſte</l>
                     <l>I counſell thee haue lykewyſe dredde.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Themiſtocles, none ill had wrought,</l>
                     <l>VVhen he ſo often letters ſent:</l>
                     <l>To Pawſanye, yet ſome folkes thought</l>
                     <l>To traye the realme, was his intent.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>If any man thee charge therefore,</l>
                     <l>VVith thynges vntrue in euery part,</l>
                     <l>Be negligent no whit the more,</l>
                     <l>Nor lightly let them from thee ſtart.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <pb facs="tcp:176515:23"/>
                     <l>But take good hede, leſt thou or thyne,</l>
                     <l>Hath geuen ſome cauſe, of ſuche ill fame,</l>
                     <l>VVhiche once founde out, thy ſelfe enclyne,</l>
                     <l>To learne, thencefoorth to flee theſame.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>For ſuch ill happes as comes vnwares</l>
                     <l>Do oft times teache, what is for vs,</l>
                     <l>Moſt mete to doe, in ſuch lyke cares,</l>
                     <l>As Merop ſaith in writing thus.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>VVhen fortune did me cleane depriue</l>
                     <l>Of that, whiche I eſtemed moſt:</l>
                     <l>To muche more wit I did arriue</l>
                     <l>Albeit full dere it did me coſt.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>By maiſters then of cheaper price</l>
                     <l>VVhiche be our foes, why ſhould we ſteke</l>
                     <l>In thynges vnknowen to take aduyce,</l>
                     <l>VVhiche with ſuch coſt we ſometyme ſeke.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>For they in vs doe knowe and ſee</l>
                     <l>A thouſande thynges, whiche frendes reiect,</l>
                     <l>Becauſe by loue they blinded bee,</l>
                     <l>VVhere foes are full of great reſpect.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>When Hierons foe did hym reproue,</l>
                     <l>For that his breth did ſauer ill:</l>
                     <l>Then to his wife, and beſt beloue,</l>
                     <l>With ſpede went he to chide his fill.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <pb facs="tcp:176515:24"/>
                     <l>And ſayde to her, why haſt thou not,</l>
                     <l>To me declarde this fault of myne?</l>
                     <l>Becauſe (quoth ſhe) I thought god wot,</l>
                     <l>That all mens brethes had bene as thine.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Thus may you ſee, that frendes moſt deare</l>
                     <l>Our faultes nought can, ſo ſoone out fynde</l>
                     <l>As foes that aye, both farre and neare:</l>
                     <l>Fayles not to kepe ſuche thynges in mynde.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>One vertue more, and that full goode</l>
                     <l>By foes alſo we maye obtayne:</l>
                     <l>VVhiche is, our tonges in angry moode,</l>
                     <l>By reaſons bytte for to refraine.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>For vertues ſuch wyll not be hadde,</l>
                     <l>Except we learne in tyme to tame,</l>
                     <l>Our fierce affectes, and rageing madde,</l>
                     <l>VVherby oftimes, we come to ſhame.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>As loe, beholde, the wrathfull man,</l>
                     <l>For lacke of wyt and temperaunce,</l>
                     <l>His fooliſh woordes, to ſtay nought can:</l>
                     <l>VVhereof doth ſpring muche variaunce.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>This fault therfore, as Plato ſayes,</l>
                     <l>Both god and man, dothe chaſt doubtles:</l>
                     <l>For that the reſt at all aſſayes,</l>
                     <l>It doth excede in peuiſhnes.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <pb facs="tcp:176515:24"/>
                     <l>But ſilence is, without all harme,</l>
                     <l>And tonges to heare, that lewdly raue</l>
                     <l>With ſtoutnes ſuch, it ſelfe doth arme:</l>
                     <l>As Socrates was wont to haue.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Yea rather more as Hercules</l>
                     <l>For as they ſay, no wordes of ſpight,</l>
                     <l>Coulde once offende his hardines:</l>
                     <l>But as a flye them wayde ſo lyght.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>What thynge therefore more graue may be,</l>
                     <l>Then ſtyll to be, whilſt foes do rayle,</l>
                     <l>As when we woulde take hede to fle:</l>
                     <l>Some fearefull rocke, wherby we ſayle</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Beſydes all this, thou ſhalt thus leare,</l>
                     <l>Thy brawlynge wyfe, and chydinge frend</l>
                     <l>Thy brothers faultes with eaſe to beare,</l>
                     <l>Howe muche ſoeuer they offend.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>I only ſpeake of theſe, I ſay,</l>
                     <l>Becauſe I do my ſelfe aſſure,</l>
                     <l>Thy parentes woordes and ſtripes alway,</l>
                     <l>Without all grudge thou wilt endure.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>For what intent dyd Socrates</l>
                     <l>His frowarde wyfe, Zantip by name</l>
                     <l>At home retayne, but patientnes</l>
                     <l>To learne: abrode to vſe the ſame.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <pb facs="tcp:176515:25"/>
                     <l>Muche better wert ſuche pacience</l>
                     <l>To learne by ſuffryng aye thy foe:</l>
                     <l>Whoſe ſpightfull woordes with ill pretence</l>
                     <l>Do count as wynde, and let them goe.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>In enmitie, thus you may ſee,</l>
                     <l>That pacience mylde hath greateſt grace</l>
                     <l>But frendſhip ſekes ſimplicitee</l>
                     <l>And frendly dedes doth moſt embrace</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Nor it deſerues ſo great a prayſe</l>
                     <l>Thy faithfull frende to gratefie:</l>
                     <l>As it is foule when nede aſſayes</l>
                     <l>Of frendly helpe, hym to denye.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Our foes offence if we ſet lyght,</l>
                     <l>When iuſt reuenge in vs doth lye:</l>
                     <l>It demed is in eche mans ſight</l>
                     <l>A dede, whiche doth our vertue trye.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>But moſt renowne to him is due,</l>
                     <l>Who, as his owne, his foes diſgrace</l>
                     <l>With wofull heart doth wayle and rue,</l>
                     <l>And hym to helpe doth haſt a pace.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>And eke his prompt to doe no leſſe</l>
                     <l>When that he ſeeth his wife or chylde,</l>
                     <l>His man or maide in great diſtreſſe</l>
                     <l>And praying ayde with woordes full mylde.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <pb facs="tcp:176515:25"/>
                     <l>For ſtony heartes haue they ywis</l>
                     <l>That would not praiſe ſo great a grace:</l>
                     <l>And thinke him worthy all mens bliſſe,</l>
                     <l>That mercy ſuche wyll than embrace.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>VVhen Ceſar made the Pictures faire,</l>
                     <l>Of Pompey to be ſet againe,</l>
                     <l>That downe were caſte out of their chayre,</l>
                     <l>Muche praiſe thereby he did than gayne.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>For Tully ſayde, O worthy wight,</l>
                     <l>By tendring thus, thy foes renowne</l>
                     <l>Thou haſte thyne owne, ſo well yplight:</l>
                     <l>As neuer power ſhall throwe it downe.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>VVherefore I ſay thy mortall foe</l>
                     <l>VVhich doth deſerue to haue great lande</l>
                     <l>Depriue thou not vniuſtly tho:</l>
                     <l>By ſpyghtfull meanes, or wicked fraude.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Sythe that the more thou doeſt him prayſe,</l>
                     <l>The greater prayſe thou ſhalt obtayne,</l>
                     <l>Beſides beliefe, when to dyſpraiſe</l>
                     <l>Thou ſhalt diſpoſed be agayne.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>For no man than, wyll iudge or deme,</l>
                     <l>That thou doeſt hate his perſonage:</l>
                     <l>But rather as doth beſt beſeme,</l>
                     <l>Doſt hate his vice, and yll vſage.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <pb facs="tcp:176515:26"/>
                     <l>The beſt yet is, that by this way</l>
                     <l>Non enuye ſhall in vs remayne:</l>
                     <l>Ne ſhall we grudge to heare men ſay</l>
                     <l>Our frende to be full iuſt and playne.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Or all men els texcell and paſſe,</l>
                     <l>In this or that good qualite,</l>
                     <l>Wherat the ſpightfull hearte alas,</l>
                     <l>Woulde freat, and ryght ſore moued be.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>What vertue than more profitable</l>
                     <l>Or goodly, may our myndes retayne</l>
                     <l>Than this, wherby, we be made hable:</l>
                     <l>To purge the venome of diſdayne.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>In common weales, ſome ill decrees,</l>
                     <l>Ill cuſtome doth ſo well approue</l>
                     <l>That thoughe therby ſome loſe their fees:</l>
                     <l>Yet none with eaſe maye them remoue.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>In enmite lykewyſe we ſee</l>
                     <l>Be many faultes, as hatefull ſpight,</l>
                     <l>Of others grieues right gladde to bee</l>
                     <l>Beſides ſuſpect both daye and night.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>The callinge eke of wronges to minde,</l>
                     <l>And many other hurtfull vyce,</l>
                     <l>As frawde, and guyle, and meanes to finde,</l>
                     <l>To traytours traynes our foe tentyce.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <pb facs="tcp:176515:26"/>
                     <l>Which thinges full oft to vſe with foes</l>
                     <l>We take it as none ill doutles:</l>
                     <l>And whilſt our mindes we ſo diſpoſe,</l>
                     <l>Our faultes remaine without redreſſe.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>For if we neuer vſe tabſtaine,</l>
                     <l>Againſt our foes ſuch partes to play:</l>
                     <l>Ill cuſtome ſhall vs eke conſtrayne,</l>
                     <l>Our frendes to dreſſe in like aray.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Pithagoras did men denye,</l>
                     <l>To hunt, to hawke, or birde to ſlea</l>
                     <l>And fiſhe in net would often bye,</l>
                     <l>To caſt againe into the ſea.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>No bruit beaſt eke, of gentle race</l>
                     <l>Would he haue ſlayne in any wiſe</l>
                     <l>Leſt fierce affectes we ſhould imbrace</l>
                     <l>Through ſuch a cruell exerciſe.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>More goodly, yet it were to flee</l>
                     <l>Such euill affectes throughe ſufferaunce</l>
                     <l>And ſhewing oft our ſelues to bee</l>
                     <l>Right iuſt to foes in variaunce.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>So ſhall we vſe no kynde of guyle</l>
                     <l>Ne fraude with frendes in their affares</l>
                     <l>But ſhall be playne and thinke it vyle</l>
                     <l>One worde vnkinde, to ſpeake vnwares.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <pb facs="tcp:176515:27"/>
                     <l>When Scaurus at the lawe did ſewe,</l>
                     <l>Domitius his mortall foe:</l>
                     <l>Domitius a ſlaue vntrewe,</l>
                     <l>Had then with him that fled him fro.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Whiche ſlaue forthwith to Scaurus went,</l>
                     <l>His mayſters ſecretes, to diſcloſe,</l>
                     <l>But Scaurus ſeeyng his intent:</l>
                     <l>His eares full faſt, dyd ſtop and cloſe.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>And nought would heare againſt his foe,</l>
                     <l>By ſuche a wretche, as woulde hym tray,</l>
                     <l>Yea, more he bound hym faſt alſo:</l>
                     <l>And home agayne hym ſent ſtraight way.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>VVhen Cato lykewyſe matter ſought</l>
                     <l>Againſt Muren to fortefie</l>
                     <l>Thaccuſement late before hym brought,</l>
                     <l>He nothyng dyd maliciouſly.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>For ſuche as after hym dyd goe,</l>
                     <l>(As was the wont) to heare and ſee:</l>
                     <l>If that ſelfe day, dyd aſke hym tho,</l>
                     <l>The matter ſhoulde diſcuſſed be:</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>To whom when he had once ſayde nay,</l>
                     <l>They by and by did all depart,</l>
                     <l>And thought it true whiche he did ſay,</l>
                     <l>Suche faith of hym was in their hart.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <pb facs="tcp:176515:27"/>
                     <l>But Simond ſaith, as euery larke,</l>
                     <l>Of force muſt haue his coppid creaſt:</l>
                     <l>So natures gifte, yf ye well marke,</l>
                     <l>Some ſpight doth brede, in eche mans breaſt.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>For whiche emongeſt light frendes, it were</l>
                     <l>Right good, as Pyndar doth ſuppoſe:</l>
                     <l>Of ill affectes, our myndes to cleare</l>
                     <l>by powring them into our foes.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>And as a ſinke our foes temploy</l>
                     <l>Our filthy faultes to kepe in ſtore,</l>
                     <l>The ſtenche wherof might els annoy</l>
                     <l>Our faithfull frendes, and grieue them ſore.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>In Syo ſprang one tyme ſuche ſtrife</l>
                     <l>That all the towne in factions twaine</l>
                     <l>Deuyded was: then was in lyfe,</l>
                     <l>Onomadem, a man full playne.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>And curteous eke to euery wight,</l>
                     <l>VVho chaunced on that ſide to be</l>
                     <l>That wan the fielde by force of fight,</l>
                     <l>To whom he gaue this counſell free.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Expell not all (quoth he) your dede</l>
                     <l>That did reſiſt: but ſome retayne,</l>
                     <l>Leſt lacke of foes, may hatred brede,</l>
                     <l>Emongſt our ſelues, vnto our payne.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <pb facs="tcp:176515:28"/>
                     <l>Heſiode ſayth, wheras lyke arte</l>
                     <l>Nigh neighbored, or kyndred is</l>
                     <l>The good ſucceſſe of eyther parte,</l>
                     <l>Eche one tenuye it wer amiſſe.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>But yf you can none other waye</l>
                     <l>From ſpight abſtayne, accuſtome than</l>
                     <l>The welthy ſtate and good araye</l>
                     <l>Of thoſe your foes, to curſe and ban.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>For lyke as gardeners good of ſkyll,</l>
                     <l>The garlyke ſtronge: by roſis ſoote</l>
                     <l>Do vſe to ſet, all ſauors yll,</l>
                     <l>From them to drawe, euen from the roote.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Our foes euen ſo that do receiue</l>
                     <l>Our frowarde faultes, our mindes full fell</l>
                     <l>Doe ridde of griefe, whiche we conceyue,</l>
                     <l>To ſe our frendes to proſpere well.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>With foes therfore we ſhould than ſtriue,</l>
                     <l>For honor, rule, and true got gayne,</l>
                     <l>And not to freat when that they thryue,</l>
                     <l>Or more than we, do chaunce tattaine.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Ye rather more we ſhould obſerue</l>
                     <l>Their doinges all in euery caſe,</l>
                     <l>And howe they did ſuch thinges deſerue,</l>
                     <l>That learne we might them how to paſſe.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <pb facs="tcp:176515:28"/>
                     <l>Themiſtocles was wont to tell</l>
                     <l>He could not ſlepe for thinking on</l>
                     <l>The victorie, that whylome fell</l>
                     <l>Milthiad to, in Marathon.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>It is a ſlouthfull grudge and hate,</l>
                     <l>The vertues of thy foes to ſpight:</l>
                     <l>And none of them to imitate</l>
                     <l>Becauſe thou thinkeſt they paſſe thy might.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>But where as hate thy iudgemente clere</l>
                     <l>Corrupteth not his diligence:</l>
                     <l>And induſtrie doth then appere,</l>
                     <l>Which driues away thy negligence.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>But if he ſeme in Prynces hall,</l>
                     <l>Or common weale, right hygh eſtate</l>
                     <l>To haue hym got by ſeruice thrall</l>
                     <l>Or flattring meanes, reioyce thereat.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>And thinke thy ſelfe an happy wight,</l>
                     <l>For that thou mayſt thy honeſt lyfe:</l>
                     <l>Compare with his in all mens ſight</l>
                     <l>And win great praiſe withouten ſtrife.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>For Plato ſaith, no golde on earth</l>
                     <l>Or vnder earth, ne precious ſton:</l>
                     <l>One ſparke of vertue can be worth,</l>
                     <l>Whiche paſſeth all compariſon.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <pb facs="tcp:176515:29"/>
                     <l>Ne Solon eke, would chaunge his ſtate</l>
                     <l>In vertue fixt for vain renowne</l>
                     <l>Ne did he care to be check mate</l>
                     <l>VVith noble men in euery towne.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>He ſtemed not the peoples prayſe</l>
                     <l>Whoſe wandryng wyttes are lyke the wynde</l>
                     <l>Nowe heare nowe there at all aſſayſe</l>
                     <l>Their yea, with nay, full ſone tonbynde.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>No worthy ſtate that ſemes to bee,</l>
                     <l>Can worthy be, in verye dede</l>
                     <l>Except the meanes therto perdee</l>
                     <l>Of worthy actes dyd firſt procede.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>But lyke as loue, doth louers blynde</l>
                     <l>Euen ſo we ſpye, the faultes of foes</l>
                     <l>Much farther of, than we can fynde</l>
                     <l>The faultes of frendes before our noes</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Reioyce not than with ioye in vayne</l>
                     <l>Becauſe thy foe doth chaunce toffende,</l>
                     <l>Ne take no griefe without ſome gaine,</l>
                     <l>To ſe what good his workes pretende.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>But ponder well theſe caſes twayne,</l>
                     <l>His vice and vertues both I ſay</l>
                     <l>And firſt his vyce from vyce tabſtaine</l>
                     <l>And therin paſſe him farre away.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <pb facs="tcp:176515:29"/>
                     <l>His vertues than thou ſhalt doe well</l>
                     <l>To imitate in their degree:</l>
                     <l>And though thou canſt not hym excell</l>
                     <l>Yet ſee thou be not worſe than hee.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <trailer>Finis.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
            <back>
               <div type="colophon">
                  <p>¶ Imprinted at London by Wyllyam Seres, dwellynge at the weſt ende of Poules, at the Sygne of the Hedgehogge. Anno. 1561.</p>
               </div>
            </back>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:176515:30"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:176515:30"/>
                  <p>¶ The porte of reſte.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="poem">
                  <pb facs="tcp:176515:31"/>
                  <l>Lyke as the mightie Oke whoſe rootes,</l>
                  <l>In thearth are fixed faſt:</l>
                  <l>Is hable to withſtande eache winde,</l>
                  <l>That blowes moſt boyſtrous blaſt.</l>
                  <l>Euen ſo eache frowarde Fortunes happe</l>
                  <l>That euer maie betyde:</l>
                  <l>The conſtant minde with vertue fraught</l>
                  <l>is hable to abyde.</l>
               </div>
               <div type="poem">
                  <pb facs="tcp:176515:31"/>
                  <head>¶ To the true louers of wiſe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dome Iohn Aſteley, mayſter of the Queenes Maieſtyes Iewell houſe, and Iohn Harington Eſquier Thomas Blun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deuille, greeting.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>WHilſt plutarks works, I gaue my ſelf to rede</l>
                     <l>So pleaſant fruit me thought, I could none fid</l>
                     <l>As is in y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> which rightly ſhewes in dede</l>
                     <l>The waie tappeaſe, and ſtill thunquiete minde.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>For wheras ſince falſe flattring hope with who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     </l>
                     <l>I trauelde had, long tyme full painfully,</l>
                     <l>Of comforte voide, alone me leaft to rome</l>
                     <l>The barrein coſte of wretched miſerye:</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>In ſtead of helping me the ſeas to paſſe</l>
                     <l>Of worldly ioyes, amongſt the happy ſorte,</l>
                     <l>In ſhip full fraught with fortunes giftes: as was</l>
                     <l>Her vowe when firſt to me ſhe did reſorte:</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>The reſtles muſe had made my feble brayn</l>
                     <l>The forge of care, and therein daily wroughte</l>
                     <l>Such dulfull domps &amp; d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>eadful dreames as cleane</l>
                     <l>From mirth my mind vnto deſpaire had brought.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>That boke did yeld ſuch gliſtring beames Iſay.</l>
                     <l>Of comfort great and ioyfull quietnes:</l>
                     <l>As draue thoſe dumpes and ſorowes all away</l>
                     <l>My heauy heart which helde in great diſtres.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <pb facs="tcp:176515:32"/>
                     <l>So as in dede from that time foorth me thought</l>
                     <l>I coulde not chuſe but nedes contented reſt</l>
                     <l>And though before vaine hope much griefe hadde wrought</l>
                     <l>Yet now to think y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> al was for the beſt.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Which comfort though it grateful was to me</l>
                     <l>In my conceyt yet did it not ſuffiſe:</l>
                     <l>Onleſſe that you my faithfull frendes might be</l>
                     <l>Eke partners of the ſame ſome kinde of wiſe.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>For as the grief of one frende dothe decreace</l>
                     <l>His other frendes, when they therof partake</l>
                     <l>His ioye euen ſo he ſhall the more encreace</l>
                     <l>If of theſame, he doth them partners make.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Into our tunge therfore this litle quaire</l>
                     <l>I turned haue, and termd the port of reſt</l>
                     <l>And wiſhe eche wight, therto for to repaire</l>
                     <l>with troubled ſprite that feeles himſelf oppreſt.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>For as the mariner, in ſea whoſe bote</l>
                     <l>With cruel ſtormes and tempeſts hath been beat</l>
                     <l>And drieue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> twixt whaues &amp; feareful rocks to flote</l>
                     <l>Though al that while diſpaire his mind did freat:</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Yet whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> winds their boiſtrous blowing ceace</l>
                     <l>And he to hauen is ſafely come at laſt</l>
                     <l>He than reioyceth with himſelf in peace</l>
                     <l>And cleane forgeates al thoſe his daungers paſt:</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <pb facs="tcp:176515:32"/>
                     <l>Euen ſo eche man within this litle port</l>
                     <l>That ſhall voucheſafe at times more ydley ſpente</l>
                     <l>To harborough a while: himſelfe to ſport</l>
                     <l>When he perceiues his minde to ſorow bent:</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>To warrant him I dare be bolde I ſaie</l>
                     <l>That though he be in paſſing heauines</l>
                     <l>Yet he thereby ſhall quickly learne the waie</l>
                     <l>To rid his minde of all vnquietnes.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Ne ſhall he feare the loſſe in time to come</l>
                     <l>Of frendes, of goodes, of lyfe, or lyke diſtres</l>
                     <l>But lyue and dye, by helpe of reaſons dome</l>
                     <l>In ſuche aſſured holde of quietnes:</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>As neyther frowarde fortunes ſharpe aſſaultes,</l>
                     <l>Nor death himſelf, for all his dreadfull name</l>
                     <l>Ne malice eke with all her forged faultes</l>
                     <l>Shall be of power to ouerthrowe theſame.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>To you therefore to whom I am muche bounde</l>
                     <l>And tall the reſt, lo here nowe for your ſake</l>
                     <l>Of this my paine ſuche fruite as hath redounde</l>
                     <l>In frendly wiſe I doe a preſent make.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Whoſe relles though it be not halfe ſo ſwete</l>
                     <l>Ne hath ſuche ſappe of eloquence in dede</l>
                     <l>As thoſe thinges haue whereon (as meates moſt mete</l>
                     <l>For deintie mouthes) you wonted are to fede.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <pb facs="tcp:176515:33"/>
                     <l>Yet doubt I not but that voucheſafe you wyll,</l>
                     <l>To take it well in woorth, and ſpeciallye</l>
                     <l>Sithe Budes woordes in all this treatiſe ſtyll</l>
                     <l>I folowd haue in deede moſte faithfullye.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Whoſe ſtile I founde to be more graue then gaye</l>
                     <l>And harde to turne into our vulguer ſpeche,</l>
                     <l>Yet as it is refuſe not when you maye</l>
                     <l>To taſte thereof I humbly you beſeche.</l>
                     <l>For though it hap not deintye mouthes to pleaſe</l>
                     <l>Weak ſtomakes yet thereby may find much eaſe.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="letter">
                  <pb facs="tcp:176515:33"/>
                  <head>PLVTARKE TO HIS frende Paccius.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hy letters myne owne good Paccius wherin thou didſte exhort me to write ſumwhat vnto thee, ſo well touchynge the quyetnes of the mynd, as alſo concernynge thoſe pointes in Plato his boke called Timeo: (which to thy ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming neded a more exquiſite and plainer declaratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>:) Came very late vnto my han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des. For euen as oure frende Erotes was ready to take ſhippe for to ſayle to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes Rome they were delyuered to mee in haſte, by that good man Funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus. Whereby I not hauinge time ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient to write vnto thee according to my wonte and cuſtome of ſuche thynges as thou didſt requyer: nor yet beinge hable to ſuffer ſuche a meſſenger to departe from me with emptye hande: briefly ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered certayne thynges entreatinge of the tranquility of the mynde out of ſuche Commentaries as I had written in ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes
<pb facs="tcp:176515:34"/> paſte concerninge the ſame. Tru<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtynge that in ſuche kynde of wrytinges thou wylt not looke for fyne termes and elloquent ſpeach: But onely haue regard to the good doctrine therof, whiche maye helpe to inſtruct &amp; order mans lyfe. And I thinke it already brought to ſome good paſſe. Becauſe that althoughe thou art knyt in frendſhyp (and that not after the common ſorte) with great men and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy Prynces, and haſt alſo ſuche know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and experience in matters of lawe, as thou geuiſt place to no man therein: yet for all that thou arte not lyke the tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gycall Meroppes puffed vp wyth vayne glorye, or foolyſhlye amaſed at the reioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cynge of the people, whiche hath thee in great admiration, extolling thee with in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fynite prayſes. Neyther doeſt thou for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get to haue harde oftimes howe that the ſhooe be it neuer ſo gay, can not heale the gowtye foote, nor the gold rynge the dyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe in the fynger, nor yet that the ryche Crowne of golde and ſtone can once eaſe the payne of the heade. For to whom may
<pb facs="tcp:176515:34"/> ryches, honoure, glorye, or preheminence in Court, ſerue to put away griefe of the mind, or to leade a quiet lyfe? But to ſuch, as whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they haue theſe thinges, ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vſe them, and when they lacke theim, pacie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly ſuffer the lacke therof. But howe can that be done? but onely by reaſon pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meditate, and accuſtomed immediatlye to reprehende the paſſyble, and vnrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable parte of the ſoule, ſo often as it bruſteth out, and not to ſuffer it to rau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge anye further abrode, and ſo to be turned out of the ryght way, by the vrgent pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocation of vnbrydiled affection. And therefore as Zenophon wylled all men in their proſperitie to haue moſte remen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of the Goddes, and then, moſt ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtlye and deuoutly to worſhyppe them, to thentent that the goddes beinge ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by alreadye reconcyled and rendred more fauourable towardes them, they myght afterwarde when occaſion ſhould ſerue, the boldlyer make petition, and craue the thyng that ſhould behoue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: Euen ſo al ſayinges &amp; wrytinges as be moſt apte to
<pb facs="tcp:176515:35"/> appeaſe the troubles of the minde, ought amongſt men that haue reaſon to be firſt hydde and fyxed in the mynd, to the intent that ſuche thynges beinge prepared of a longe time before, when nede ſhoulde re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quier myght ſerue them to moſt aduaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage. For as chourlyſhe maſtyffes be mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued with euerye noyſe: and yet quieted by one knowen voyce wherunto they be com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>monlye vſed: Euen ſo it is very harde for man to quiet the outragious and beſtial affectes of the mynd, except he hath ſome famylyer and accuſtomed preceptes and leſſons redye at hande to ſtyll the feruent rage therof. But ſuche as thynke that to leade a quyet lyfe, it behoueth not to do many thynges, nor to be muche occupied eyther in priuate or publyque affayres: thoſe wolde make vs to bye the tranquil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of the lyfe full deare. Syth that then, it coulde not be gotten but by ſlouth and ydlenes, exhortynge euery man therunto as thoughe he were ſycke, by that tragy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call verſe, whiche ſayth in this wyſe.</p>
                  <q>
                     <pb facs="tcp:176515:35"/>
                     <l>Abyde thou ſeely wretch, and moue not from thy bedde,</l>
                     <l>Wherin thou maieſt lye warme, &amp; eke full well befedde.</l>
                  </q>
                  <p>For yf preuye ſlouthe be to the bodye a hurtfull Medicine: than ſluggiſhnes, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licatenes, and fayntnes of corage whiche cauſeth a manne to forſake bothe kyffe, kynne, and country, is lyke wyſe as euill a phiſicion to heale the ſycknes and trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of the mynde. Moreouer it is repug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to trueth, to ſay y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thoſe men which do leaſt laboure and ſeldomiſt trauell a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brode, do leade moſt quiet lyfe. For then women ſhoulde lyue muche more quietly then men. Becauſe that women for the moſt part do tarye at home doinge lyttle, and what they do, they do it ſyttynge on theyr ſtooles. And yet as Heſiodus ſaith, thoughe the colde Northene wynde can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not by violence breake in, to blow vppon the younge and tender Damoyſelles: yet grieffes, troubles, ſorowes, and euyll diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſicions of the mynde throughe Ielou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſy, ſuperſticion, vayne glorye, &amp; ſuche lyke innumerable vyces do finde the meanes ſecretlye to creape into their preuye dor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters.
<pb facs="tcp:176515:36"/> It is ſayd alſo that Laertes forſoke his Countrey, his houſe, and the Court it ſelfe, and liued .xx. yeres in a litle Cottage all alone by him ſelfe, hauing none other compaignie, but a ſely olde woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which ſerued him of meate and drinke. And yet for all that he had both ſorowfulneſſe of heart, and heauineſſe in countenaunce, to be his compaignions mawgre his head. Yea what wyll you ſaye if this doyng of nothing, hath oft times diſturbed manye mens wits and ſences: as you may reade in Homer ſpeakinge of Achilles in thys ſort.</p>
                  <q>
                     <l>Here ſittes in ſhippe, Achilles ſwift whom Ioue begot</l>
                     <l>To fury bente, refuſing firmely nowe to fyght</l>
                     <l>Of all the Lordes &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mons eke, eſteming not</l>
                     <l>The counſels wiſe: which cauſe mans fame to ſhine full bright</l>
                     <l>He faintes in heart, and yet furthwith to fight oothe crye</l>
                     <l>And moues hymſelfe, the feates of cruell Mars to trye.</l>
                  </q>
                  <p>And therfore he being ſore greued to ſe hymſelfe ſo loſt with ydleneſſe: in a great rage reproued hym ſelfe, ſayinge in this wyſe.</p>
                  <q>
                     <l>Lo here I ſitte, full like a heauye lumpe of clay,</l>
                     <l>This Nauewe great, to kepe in ydlenes alway.</l>
                  </q>
                  <pb facs="tcp:176515:36"/>
                  <p>Wherefore Epicurus hymſelf the fau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour and mainteynor of all pleaſure and voluptuouſneſſe woulde not haue thoſe that by nature are ambicious &amp; deſirous of glory to geue themſelues to ydleneſſe: but rather to folowe nature as their guide, &amp; to ſeke to beare rule &amp; offyce in a common wealthe. For ſuche menne as be naturally enclyned to bee doyng: cannot quietlye ſuffer to be depriued of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thynge wherin they moſte delyghte. Notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyng he is vnwiſe that wyll choſe ſuche menne into a common wealth, as cannot moderate themſelues and forbeare y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> rule therof: rather then thoſe that bee hable, bothe to rule themſelues and the commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wealthe alſo. Thus then you ſee it is not meete, to meaſure the quietnes and carefulneſſe of the mynde by multytude or fewneſſe of affayres. For it is no leſſe trouble and griefe to leaue vndoone that whiche is good and honeſte, then to doe that which is nought and vile. But there be ſome whiche will preſcribe &amp; appoint themſelues before, to folowe one certain
<pb facs="tcp:176515:37"/> kynde of lyfe, which they take to be voyde of all care &amp; trouble, as to bee huſbande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menne, or to lyue vnmaried, or elles to be Prynces and rulers: whiche ſort of men how much they be deceyued, Menander dothe playnelye declare, by theſe wordes here folowynge.</p>
                  <q>I thinke, O Phania that rytche men whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che haue no nede to borowe vppon vſurye to pay their creditors, do not lye tumblyng and toſſyng in their beddes, lamentyng in the nyght ſeaſon by them ſelues, and cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge out full ofte wooe is me: but do ſleepe ſwetelye and quietlye.</q>
                  <p>But proceading a lytle further, he found the ryche to be no leſſe troubled then the poore. For life (ſayeth he) and trouble ben as it were of one kynd, and borne both at one byrthe. For trouble is compaignyon to the voluptuous and delicate lyfe, and waxeth olde with the poore &amp; miſerable lyfe. But as thoſe that be fearefull, of a weake ſtomake, and not hable to brooke the Seas: when they ſaile on the Seas, wyll remoue manye tymes out of a lyttle
<pb facs="tcp:176515:37"/> Bote into a great ſhippe and from thence into a galey, thinckynge therby to be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediatly eaſid of their griefe, vntyll ſuch time they feele that they profite nothing in ſo doinge, becauſe that whereſoeuer they go, they cary with them that Choo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler &amp; fearefulnes whych is wythin the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: Euen ſo the ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge of ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dry kindes of life cannot delyuer the mynd fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſuche grieffes and troubles as theſe be. That is to ſaye Ignoraunce, and lacke of Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience, fooliſhe raſhnes, lacke of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and power to vſe thinges preſente in their due kynde. For theſe be the thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges that v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>xe both ryche and poore, and trouble ſo well the maryed as the vnma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryed. Nor none other cauſe then thys doth make ſuche as haue forſaken the ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie for to dwell in the Country: to be wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye againe of the Countrey, and to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tourne eftſones into the Cytye. Theſe thinges alſo cauſe many men whiche by great helpe and importunate ſute, haue placed themſelues in kynges Courtes: a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>none after, to repente their laboure ſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed.
<pb facs="tcp:176515:38"/> A ſicke man as Ion ſayeth is a verye vnpleaſaunt thinge, for he cannot abyde his wyfe, he blameth his Phiſici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and is angry with his bedde. Yf hys friende commeth to vyſite him he dothe but trouble hym. And if he departe from hym, he dothe againe offende him. But after that hys dyſeaſe begynneth to aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwage and to be ſomewhat more tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate: Then commeth healthe by litle and lytle, makinge all thinges delectable and pleaſaunte. In ſuche ſorte that whereas the daye before he dyd lothe newe layde Egges, deintye Brothes, and the fyneſte breade that might be gotten: The nexte daye after, can hungerlye eate a peece of common bread, with a few creſſes. Of ſuche importaunce is a good diſcorſe in all chaunges of the life, thonely force wherof procureth the happye lyfe. It is ſayed that when Alexander hearde the Philoſopher Anaxharcus, affirmynge in diſputation, that there were innumera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble worldes: he weapte for ſorowe. And
<pb facs="tcp:176515:38"/> beynge demaunded by his frendes what iuſte cauſe he had to wepe: he aunſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rid. Haue we not iuſte cauſe (quod he) to weepe: ſythe there be ſo manye worldes and we be not as yet lordes of one? But Crates the porely clad Philoſopher, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarywiſe conſumed all hys life to the laſte daie in ſporte &amp; laughter as though they were all feſtiuall dayes. Agamem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non likewiſe kynge of the Micens was not a little troubled, for that he had the rule of ſo manye men. Of whom Homer talking ſaieth thus.</p>
                  <q>
                     <l>Thou knoweſt righte well Atreus ſon.</l>
                     <l>That clepid, is Agamemnon</l>
                     <l>Whome moſte of all with Labors great</l>
                     <l>Ioues pleaſure is, to vexe and freat.</l>
                  </q>
                  <p>When Diogenes the Phyloſopher was in the markette amongſt others to be ſolde, and was commaunded by the Cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er which ſhould ſell him to riſe vppe: He woulde not ſo doe, but ieaſted wyth the Cryer demaunding of him, if he brought a fiſhe to ſell whither he would bydde it
<pb facs="tcp:176515:39"/> riſe vppe or not? So litle he eſtemed hys myſſerable ſtate. Did not Socrates lyke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe being in priſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> faſt cheined &amp; fettred, ſtoodye wiſedome and dyſpute of phylo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophye amongſt his diſciples and Scho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars? But looke agayne on thother ſyde howe Phaeton clymyng vp into the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uens, with weeping teares complayned, becauſe that no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> would geue him the gouernement of his fathers horſe &amp; cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riot. As the ſhooe is wont to be wriethed and turned to ſerue a crooked foote, and not contrarywiſe the foote to fitte a croo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked ſhooe: Euen ſo the ſtate and diſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the mynde, muſt make euery kinde of lyfe that is offred, ſemblable and agre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng to her ſelfe. Nor it is not cuſtome as ſome men affirme, whiche maketh plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaunte the lyfe that they haue choſen as beſt for themſelues: But rather wiſedom maketh theſame life beſt, and moſte plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaunt. Therefore lette vs firſte labour to pourge, to purifie, and to make ſo cleane as is poſſible, the flowyng fountayne of the tranquilitie of the minde, whiche is
<pb facs="tcp:176515:39"/> within vs, to thintent that we may make all outwarde thinges commyng vnto vs by chaunce: plyant, and apte to ſerue the purpoſe, through our patient ſufferance. For though thinges doe not ſuccede well accordyng to oure deſire: yet it behoueth not vs to be angrie therwith, ſithe angre thereto nought appertayneth. Yea, he is to be praiſed that by arte and pollecy can ſooneſt redreſſe ſuche euyll ſucceſſe. And therefore Plato compared mans lyfe to the dice playe, in the which although the player oughte to deſier euery beſte caſte: yet howe ſo euer it chaunceth, he muſte take ſkilfull heede to diſpoſe eche caſte in the beſte wyſe that he can, according as the chaunce will beare it. Of whiche two thynges, the one, that is the chaunce of the dye, conſiſteth not in oure power. But the other lyeth in vs to perfourme. That is to ſaye if we be wiſe, to take pacientlye whatſoeuer chaunſeth, and tappoynte e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery one his right place, in ſuch ſort that whatſoeuer chaunſeth well, may bee ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied to moſt aduauntage, &amp; that whiche
<pb facs="tcp:176515:40"/> happeneth otherwiſe to leaſte damage. But fooliſhe men and vnexperte, in kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wing howe to liue: be like vnto a diſeaſed body whiche can neither ſuffer heate nor colde. For in proſperitie they be freſh and gaye, and looke pleaſauntlye. But in ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſitie they bende the browes and looke all frowardlye. And therefore both ſtates doe trouble them, yea rather in them both they trouble themſelues. And no leſſe alſo bee they troubled in thoſe thinges which of them ſelues are thoughte to bee good. Theodorus which ſurnamed is Atheus, was wonte oftetimes to ſaie, that he rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched furth his woordes with the ryghte hande, but they receaued them with the left, euen ſo fares thignorant ſort, which when fortune many tymes woulde come vnto them on the right ſide: they moſte vndecentlye turnyng themſelues awaye, doe place her on the lefte. But muche bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter doe the wiſemen, whiche lyke as bees doe make honie, whiche is of all thynges moſte ſweete, of Thyme the drieſt hearb and of moſt bitter Iuyce: So they of moſt
<pb facs="tcp:176515:40"/> harmefull thinges doe chooſe oute many tymes, ſome thinge that is to them bothe meete and profitable. Whiche thynge is moſt chiefly to be ſtudied and with much exerciſe of the minde to bee laboured. For as he that when he had throwen a ſtone at a ſnarlyng bitche, and miſſing her, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willynglye by chaunce hit his ſtepdame: ſaide vnto hymſelfe that his throwe was not altogether euill beſtowed: eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> chaunce chaunceth not according to our deſier, we maie amende it, and apply it to ſome other vſe. Diogenes was baniſhed out of his cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trey, and yet this had none euyll ſucceſſe, for the ſame baniſhemente gaue hym firſte occaſion to ſtudie Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophie. Zenon Citicus being become of a Philoſopher, a notable riche merchaunt by miſfortune loſte all that he had ſaue one ſhippe, whiche afterwarde, when he heard that it was alſo loſte by tempeſte in the Sea, together with all his monne and marchandiſe fraighted in the ſame: he ſaide.</p>
                  <q>
                     <pb facs="tcp:176515:41"/>O Fortune how nobly haſt thou dealt with me, thus to driue me vnto the Philoſophical hauen, and to weare again that vnaccuſtomed apparel.</q>
                  <p>What dothe lette vs then but that we maye take example at theſe men and fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe them? Haſte thou bene depriued of anye office in the citie? goe then into the countrey, and attende thyne own priuate affayres. Haſt thou by importunate ſute, labour to creepe into thy Princes fauor, and ſuffered crepulſe therin? Thou ſhalt then thereby liue in ſafetie, &amp; free from al maner of charge and commiſſion of hys affaires. But perhappes contrarywyſe, thou art troubled with to manye offyces &amp; wrapte in too many cares: I ſay to thee that warme water dothe not ſo muche nooriſhe and comforte the tender and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licate bodye (as ſayeth Pyndarus) as ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor, and glorie, ioyned with power, and aucthoritie, dothe make laboure to ſeeme pleaſaunt, and eaſily employed. But thou art offended and grieued becauſe others do talke of thee, or beare thee enuy, or vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuſtlye ſlaunder thee: well, this is but a proſperous wynde meete to carye thee
<pb facs="tcp:176515:41"/> vnto the Muſis and into thuniuerſities. As it chaunced to Plato, at ſuche times as he was taken vnwares with the fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of Dioniſius, as though it had bene with a cruel ſtorme or tempeſt. And ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it helpeth not a litle towardes y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eting of the minde, diligently to note and to marke thexamples of the worthie and famous men, whether perchaunce they haue ſuffred the lyke euyll at anye tyme, through the lyke occaſion. As for exaum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, the loſſe of thy children doeth grieue thee: beholde then the Kynges of Rome, wherof there was not one that left a ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne behind him to enherite y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kingdo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e. Thou canſt not paciently endure pouertie: who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> then wouldeſt thou wiſh to be amongſte the Boetians, rather the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Epaminondas, or amongſt the Romains, rather the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>britius? But putte caſe thy wife bee nought of her bodie. Well, doeſt thou not knowe that Epigram of Aegides which is in Delphos? Haſte thou not heard alſo howe that Alcibiades defiled Aegides wife called Timea, and howe ſhe her ſelf
<pb facs="tcp:176515:42"/> was wont to cal the childe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſhe brought furth Alcibiades, and to whiſper in her maydens eares that they lykewiſe ſhould ſo cal him? and yet Aegides was no more letted by this, to proue a right noble and famous man: then Stilpo the Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher was letted by the vnchaſtnes of his daughter, to leade a merier lyfe then all the Philoſophers in his tyme. Whyche thing being afterwards caſt in his teeth, by one Metrocles: is then ſaieth he, thys my faulte, or my daughters? The other anſwered, that the fault was his daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, but the euill chaunce and miſhappe was his. How can that be (quoth he?) For be not faultes necligent, ouerſightes and humain frailties? The other aunſwered, yes in deede. But then (quoth Stilpo,) be not the necligente ouerſightes the errors alſo of them that be ouerſeen? Metrocles aunſwered, yes certainly. Why then ſaid Stilpo ſhould not therrours be the myſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunes of thoſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> haue ſo erred? By ſuch kind of pleaſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t talk &amp; Philoſophical qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etnes he declared the obiectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of thother
<pb facs="tcp:176515:42"/> to be no other thing, but the ſlaunderous talk &amp; vain barkinges of a curriſh felow. There be many alſo that be not only mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued with the vices of their frendes &amp; kinſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>folkes, but alſo with thoſe of their ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies. For wheras opprobrious woordes, anger, enuy, diſhoneſtie, ſpightfull ielou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, ſhuld moſt chiefly diſtain thoſe me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in whom thei raigne: yet the ſelf ſame vices trouble alſo &amp; moue thignorant ſorte, no leſſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the diſpleaſures of theyr owne kinſfolks, or the frowardnes of their fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des &amp; familiars, or the wicked wittes &amp; e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uil diſpoſed mindes of theyr owne ſlaues &amp; ſeruantes, wherwith thou thy ſelfe al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo as it ſeemeth to me, art wont to be mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued. For as thoſe Phiſicions that be me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cioned in Sophocles do purge bitter cho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ler with a bitter medicine: eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo thou art wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to be angry with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> diſeaſes &amp; naugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty diſpoſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of other mens myndes, &amp; w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> like bitternes of thine own mind (which is litle to thi worſhip) to anſwer the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And therfore thoſe thinges which thou doeſt, be not done w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a gentle &amp; plaine behauior,
<pb facs="tcp:176515:43"/> the meeteſt inſtrumente for the purpoſe, but for the moſt part after a rough, croo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, and frooward ſort? And as to correct this faulte, is more then thou canſt well performe: ſo it is alſo in dede not very ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſy to be done. But if thou couldeſt applye thoſe thinges to their right vſe wherun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to they were ordeyned, like as Chyrurgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans do their toothe drawing inſtrume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, their lau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cing kniues, &amp; cloſinge boocles, and ſhewe in thy ſelfe ſuche meekeneſſe &amp; modeſtie euery where according as occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion dothe requier: thou ſhouldeſt bee no more offended with the leude behauiour and wickedneſſe of others, then reioyced within thy ſelfe with the conſcience of thyne owne affection. For thou ſhouldeſt thinke it no more vnmeete for ſuche per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſones ſo to dooe: then it is vnnaturall for dogges to barke. But yf thou be ſo feable and weake of courage that thou wilt ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer thy ſelfe to bee oppreſt by other mens euils: nombers of griefes flowynge into thee, as into an abiect place lowe couched &amp; apt to receiue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame, ſhall ouerwhelme
<pb facs="tcp:176515:43"/> thee, thou miſerable man waxinge euery daie more ſicker the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> other. Yea what wil you ſaye, yf manye of the Phyloſophers haue reproued the compaſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wherwith we are moued when we ſee anye man in miſerie, affirmyng it to be the parte of a good manne, to helpe his kinſfolkes and neighbours, when they be afflicted with miſery, and are by fortune ouerthrowen: but not to be partakers of their ſorow, or to yelde to fortune with like ſubiectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the mynde. Yea and that whiche to euery mans iudgement ſeemeth a greate deale more ſtraunge. Though we knowe oure ſelues to haue offended and to bee of a naughtie diſpoſition: yet for all that they wyll not ſuffer vs to bee ſorowfull in our mynd for the ſame, becauſe thoſe thinges ought to be corrected and amended (ſaye they) without griefe or heauineſſe of the mynde. If thinges be thus, conſider well whether it bee not a foule thyng for vs to be diſpleaſed and angry, whenſoeuer a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny man with whom we haue to do, doth perhappes deale with vs ſomewhat vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gentlye
<pb facs="tcp:176515:44"/> or extremely. But I feare me (O moſt frendly Paccius y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſelf loue doth de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue vs, &amp; that we be not ſo muche grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued with other mens offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces, as pleaſed with our owne deſertes. For the veheme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t affecting &amp; inordinate folowynge of cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain things, or contrarywiſe thauoiding &amp; abhorring of the ſame, otherwyſe then honeſtie requireth: dothe breede manye times debate and ſtrife amongſt me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and cauſeth the one to be offended with the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, whileſt thone doth attribute to tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers fault, for that he hath bene preuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of this commoditie, or hath fallen in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to that daunger. But if a man coulde ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordinge to the ſucceſſe of thinges vſe to frame himſelf euery waye in a moderate ſort: that man with great facilitie might learne to liue with all men in all places. But nowe let vs returne againe to thoſe thinges, from the whiche we haue for a while digreſſed. As thoſe that bee ſicke of an ague to whom all thinges dooe ſeeme bitter ſo ſoone as they taſte thereof, vntyll they ſee that others without makyng a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
<pb facs="tcp:176515:44"/> ſigne of bitter taſte, dooe gredelye eate thoſe meates which they did ſo lothſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſpit out: do no lenger the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> attribute the fault to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> meate or to the drink, but to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues &amp; to their ſicknes: euen ſo if we ſee that others with great quietnes of mind &amp; with a mery countenance, do performe the ſelfeſame thynges which we paſſe o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer with greate regreate and ſorowfull complaintes: let vs the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> leaue at length to be ſo muche greued and offended with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thynges themſelues. But for to reteygne a conſtant mynde in tyme of aduerſitie, it is verye neceſſarie and expediente, not to paſſe ouer with winking eyes thoſe thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges which luckely according to oure deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er at any time haue chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ced vnto vs, &amp; ſo with a meete mixture y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> euill miſhaps, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> happye happes to reco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>penſe. To recreate our eyes, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thei bee daſeled with ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much beholding of gliſtering things, we vſe to turne the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> away, &amp; to behold pleaſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t grene herbs &amp; floures. And yet our minds we do co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trarywiſe diſpoſe to Mela<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>choly &amp; ſorowfull thynges, forceyng it to haue
<pb facs="tcp:176515:45"/> remembraunce of thinges moſt worthye repentaunce, and by violence we pul it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waye whether it wyll or not from ſuche thynges as are to be commended &amp; prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed. And nowe it commeth to my remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braunce, that to this purpoſe may be ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry well applied the ſayinge whiche was ſometyme ſpoken againſte a curious fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe that buſilye ſearched after other mens matters nothynge apperteynynge vnto him.</p>
                  <q>Why a miſchief doeſt thou moſt ſpightful ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with kites eyes ſo narrowlye marke other mens faultes, and with the eyes of an Owle blindly paſſeſt ouer thine owne.</q>
                  <p>Euen ſo thou happye man, why doeſt thou ſo diligently regard thy griefes and euyll miſhappes, makyng them alwayes preſente and freſhe before thyne eyes by continuall remembraunce, and turneſte thy mynde from preſent ioye and proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie. And lyke as ſcaryfyinge cuppes wherewyth Phiſitians vſe to drawe the fouleſt bloud out of the fleſh: ſo thou doeſt gather thy woorſt thynges into thy ſelf.
<pb facs="tcp:176515:45"/> Being in that caſe no better then y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant of Syo, who though he ſold much wyne, yea and that principall good to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers: yet ſought out alwayes for himſelf that which was ſoure and without ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure. Whoſe ſeruaunte beyng on a tyme fledde from him was demaunded of one what cauſe had conſtrayned hym to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake his maiſter? becauſe (quoth he) my maiſter hauing good thinges in his cuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tody wil take no part therof, but alwaies for himſelfe ſeeketh the woorſt. There be many lyke this man, whiche forſakynge the ſweeteſt drinkes doe take them vnto the ſowreſt and moſt harſhe of taſte. But Ariſtippus did not ſo, who beinge placed as it were betwixte a paire of ballaunce, would not diſcende into the heauieſt and moſt preſte downe with euils, but moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vp to the higheſte and leaſt chargied with griefe. For when he had loſt the ple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſanteſte lordſhip that he had: he ſpake to one of thoſe men which ſhowed the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues to be very ſorie for the loſſe thereof and to lament muche his fortune: in thys wiſe.
<pb facs="tcp:176515:46"/> Doeſt thou not know (quoth he) that thou haſt but one litle ferme to liue on, and I haue three manours with the demeanes yet left hole vnto my ſelf? that is true ſaid the other. Why, then (quoth he) ſhould not I be rather ſory for thee, then thou for me? For it is very mad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>es to bee ſorye for things loſt, &amp; not to reioyce in thinges ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued. And as litle children whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> any man, of many thinges taketh but one litle tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fle from them doe weepe and crye out ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtyng all the reſt awaie: euen ſo we being in any one lytle thinge by fortune diſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed: we lament and complaine reiectynge all the reſt as vnprofitable. But ſome ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> perchaunce would ſaie what haue we to reioyce in? yea rather, what haue we not? This manne hathe greate honour, that manne a faire houſe, this manne a wyfe, according to his mynde, that manne a faythfull frende. Antipater tarſenſis countynge in hys deathe bedde vppon hys fyngers all the good thynges that euer he hadde in hys lyfe tyme: dyd not omytte ſo muche as hys proſperous ſai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lynge
<pb facs="tcp:176515:46"/> oute of Cilitia vnto Athens. Nor theſe common thynges oughte to be neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected, yea we ought to make ſome compt of them. As for that we lyue and bee in healthe alſo for that we ſee the Sunne, and that there is neyther warre nor ſedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion, that the lande is errable, and the Sea eaſye for euerye manne to ſaile on, finally for that it is free for vs to ſpeake, and to keepe ſylence to bee occupy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and to bee ydle. But the preſence of theſe thynges woulde gieue vs the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter occaſion of quietneſſe: if we woulde fyxe in oure mynde the Image of thab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence and lacke of the ſame. Oftentimes admonyſhynge oure ſelues howe great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye healthe is deſyred of them that bee ſycke, and peace wyſhed for of thoſe that bee troubled with warre. And howe muche the ſtraungyer beynge of lowe degree, deſyereth to gette honour and fame in ſuche a noble Citye, and agayne howe bitter a thyng it is to loſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> which was once gotten. For in mine oppinion none of theſe thynges, or ſuche lyke,
<pb facs="tcp:176515:47"/> ought to be eſtemed or wiſhed for, beynge once loſt: ſithe that nothing is to bee the more regarded for that it leaueth to haue his being: nether yet ought we to poſſeſſe theſe thinges as thinges of excellencye or to kepe them with ſuche carefulnes, wat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching them continually leaſt we ſhoulde be ſpoiled of them as of thinges of pryce: yea rather though we ſafely poſſeſſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, yet as tranſitorie thinges we oughte to neglecte them and litle regarde them. For theſe thinges ought to be vſed and enioy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ed with pleaſure, and chiefly to thentent that if we ſhould chance to loſe them: we might the more quietly and moderately ſuffer the loſſe thereof. But many as Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſilaus ſaith, thinke it labour well be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed one man to come after another in courſe and order for to beholde with fix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed eye, and minde, the poeſies, pictures, &amp; ymages of others: neglecting their owne lyfe, whiche though it hath many conſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deracions and aduertiſementes and that not vnpleaſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t: yet they turnyng their eies another way, do rather conſider &amp; behold
<pb facs="tcp:176515:47"/> other mens fortunes, lyke aduouterers, whiche abhorring their owne wiues, do couet other mens, leading their lyues in great errour. For it importeth muche to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes the preſeruinge of the minde in this conſtant eſtate: firſt for a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to weye and ponder himſelf and his own peculi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er thinges, Or if he will not ſo do then to beholde and to conſider his inferiours. And not contrarywiſe as the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon ſort doth, to maruaile at thoſe whom fortune dothe extoll and aduaunce to the hygheſt degree of honoure and riches, ſo often as ſhe is diſpoſed to daly and play with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. As for example, ſuche as remaine bound and cheined in priſon, thinke thoſe to bee happy y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> be diſcharged and ſet at libertie. And thoſe that bee ſet at libertie, compte them happieſt y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> haue bene alwaies free &amp; neuer impriſoned, &amp; they that haue been alwaies free, compt them happy that bee free of the citie. Again thoſe that bee free of the citie, iudge them fortunate that bee riche. The riche, the rulers, the rulers, the kinges, the kings, the goddes, which alſo
<pb facs="tcp:176515:48"/> be not contente with their rule and king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, excepte they haue power to ſende downe lightnynge and thunder. So that when they cannot bee equall with theyr ſuperiours: they neuer keepe themſelues within their owne precinct. I care not (ſayth Thaſius) for all the riches of that notable riche manne Giges, nor dooe I muche maruayle at them, nor I ſeeke not to counterfaite the maruailous woorkes of the goddes, nor yet dooe I greately de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſier to haue rule or dominion. For theſe thynges be farre from my thoughte and cleane out of my ſight, thus ſpake Tha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſius. But loe, on the contrarye ſyde one of Syo, and alſo another of Galathia, &amp; one of Bithynia, who not contented to haue gotten honor, and offyce of rule amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gſt his Citizens: doeth yet complayne wyth weepyng teares, for that he is not one of the Senate houſe, whiche yf thou ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſte graunte hym, yet it woulde not contente hym excepte he myghte bee alſo Pretor, nor to bee Pretor, excepte hee myght bee Conſull, whiche thoughe at
<pb facs="tcp:176515:48"/> lengthe hee obteygned: yet woulde hee not bee ſatyſfyed, onleſſe hee myghte bee firſte publyſhed and proclaymed. What is thys I praye you, but a tormen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tynge and a contynuall punyſhynge of hym ſelfe, accuſynge Fortune of ingra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tytude. But the wyſe manne, thoughe of ſo greate a noumber of mortal menne: as we bee that lyue in thys worlde enioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge the lyghte of the Sunne, and are fedde wyth the fruytes of the earthe: hee ſeeth one or twoo to excell hym, eyther in honoure or rycheſſe, yet dooeth not hee for all that fytte lamentynge by hym ſelfe and wryngynge hys handes toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, but rather conſyderynge howe well he is dealte wyth, in reſpecte of an infinyte noumber that bee in myſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye: he reioyſeth wyth hym ſelfe and embraceth hys owne eſtate and condy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion of lyfe. At the Playes of pryſes, it was lawefull for no manne to procede Mayſter of fence, or to bee accompted as vanquerour, excepte he had played wyth
<pb facs="tcp:176515:49"/> euery one that came firſt to hande, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any choiſe or eleccion permitted at al. And yet in our lyfe there is ſuche varietie of thinges, that euery man hath leaue to chooſe many with whoſe eſtate he maye compare himſelfe and his eſtate. And to take therby occaſion tencourage hymſelf, &amp; to ſhewe himſelf more meete to be mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uailed at of others, then he to maruayle at them, except he be ſo impudent that he would looke to be fellowe vnto Briareus or to Hercules. And therfore whenſoeuer thou lifteſt vp thy heade to beholde anye noble manne borne a loft in a Chayer on mennes ſhoulders: caſt downe thine eyes by and by to looke alſo vppon them that beare him. Againe ſo often as thou ſhalte maruaile at Xerxes and compt him hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py, for that he had ſuche power to make a bridge ouer the ſea called Helles Pontus for him and all his armye to paſſe: conſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der then alſo the miſerable ſlaues that by ſtripes of whippes were then forced to digge in the mountain Athos, &amp; to make waie there, for the ſea to paſſe, and howe
<pb facs="tcp:176515:49"/> ſome of them were mangled and hewed, and loſte both noſe and eares, by meanes that the bridge beyng broken by rage of ſea fell down vpon them, and think that they woulde extoll thee and thy condicio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of lyfe with infinite praiſes. When a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine frende of Socrates came vppon a time vnto him complainyng y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> all things in the citie were ſolde at exceſſiue pryces, for wyne of Syo was at .xl.s. purple at vi.li. and half a pint of hony at .xx.d. So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crates takyng him by the hande brought him into the ſtorehouſe of meale, and told him that he might haue half a pinte of y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> for a halfpeny, and therefore corne was cheape. The<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he led him into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> oile ſeller, and ſhowed him that he mighte haue a pynt of that for two braſſe pence, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore quoth he all thinges in the citie bee not deare. Euen ſo if we heare anye man ſay that our eſtate is verye poore and mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable, becauſe we bee not conſulls or beare ſome other high office in the citye: we maye aunſwer him againe, that oure eſtate and condicion of life is right excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lente
<pb facs="tcp:176515:50"/> and honourable, for that wee haue no neede to begge from doore to doore, nor to beare heauye packes and burthens on oure ſhoulders as the porters dooe, nor yet lyke Paraſites to folowe and to flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter greate menne for a dyner ſake. But thoughe wee bee come to ſuche madneſſe that oure lyfe ſeemeth to depende more of other mennes, then of it ſelfe: and that oure nature is ſo degenerate, and wyth enuyous affectes corrupted, that wee bee not ſo muche reioyced wyth oure owne, as grieued wyth other mennes proſperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tye: yet I ſaye yf thou wouldeſt not onely beholde the famouſe thynges and woor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thye to bee ſeen, that are in thoſe menne, whome thou thynkeſte to bee ſo happye, and to bee as they ſaye, in goddes lappe: but alſo wouldeſt draw back that good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye fayre vayle, and outewarde ſhowe of theyr glorye, and looke further in: truely thou ſhouldeſte fynde manye of theyr in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trayles to bee ryght ſower and grieuouſe to beholde. When that Pittacus who is yet ſo famous for the greate wyſedom,
<pb facs="tcp:176515:50"/> fortytude, and Iuſtyce, wherewyth hee was endewed, enterteygned at hys Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble certayn gheaſtes whom he hadde en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyted to hys houſe: it is ſayde that hys wyfe commynge in ſodaynlye, ouerthrew the boorde in a greate rage and layed all the meate on the floore, wherewyth hee perceauyng his gheaſtes to be ſomwhat moued, ſayde thus vnto them. Euerye one of you is grieued wyth ſome kynde of euyll, and yet I in this kynde of ſtate as you ſee, dooe alwayes thynk my ſelfe maruaylouſlye well dealte wyth all. Thys manne in the Markette place is iudged to bee fortunate and happye, but ſo ſoone as hee commeth wyth in hys owne doores, hee ſeemeth to bee (I wyll not ſaye a wretche or a myſer) but euen verye myſerye it ſelfe. For there, hys wyfe poſſeſſeth all, and ruleth al imperiouſlye at her owne wyll, wyth whome hee muſte contynuallye, fyghte, chyde, and brawle, Yet ſayde hee to his ghea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes, manye thynges dooe grieue you,
<pb facs="tcp:176515:51"/> but nothing ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> grieue me at all. The like troubles be incident alſo to ſtates of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, to riche men, yea, and to kynges the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues, and yet not marked of the rude &amp; vnlearned ſorte, becauſe the courtayne of pride and glorye is drawen before theyr eyes, behinde the which al thinges lieth hidden. And therfore thei hauing regard only to the proſperitie, and not to the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſitie of other men, doe ſaye with Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer.</p>
                  <q>
                     <l>Howe happy was Agamemnon</l>
                     <l>Of all the greekes moſte woorthy wight</l>
                     <l>To whom all fate gaue place alon</l>
                     <l>Whilſte fortune gaue her childe ſuche might.</l>
                  </q>
                  <p>But this ſtraunge kinde of felicitie or happines, did conſiſte in harneſſe, horſes, and hoſtes of men gathered aboute hym, and therefore heare nowe againe, the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde voice of his ſorowfull mynde, cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing oute againſte the inſolency of ſuche glory.</p>
                  <q>
                     <l>In grieuous cares and deadly ſmart</l>
                     <l>Thus Ioue hath wrapte my woofull hart.</l>
                  </q>
                  <p>And therefore he compted thoſe moſt happy that were free from all perill, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer aduaunced to honor but dyed wyth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb facs="tcp:176515:51"/> glorie. With theſe and ſuche like kind of diſcourſes, a man by litle and litle pull out of his minde that iniquitie, which is alwaies complaining and blamyng for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune, and eleuate his deſperate mynde, whiche whileſt it hath others in admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion: doeth reiect and abaſe it ſelfe and al that it poſſeſſeth. For truely it doth great<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly breake the quiete ſtate of the mind, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a man towardes the atcheauing of anye thing doth force himſelf aboue his pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and as it were, beareth a greater ſayle then his proporcion requireth. For beyng led by a litle reioyceing hope, we raſhelye promyſe great thinges to our ſelues, and then if the ſucceſſe doe not aunſwer ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to accordingly: we accuſe fortune &amp; oure Aungell of vniuſtneſſe and partialitie. Whereas we ought rather to condemne our ſelues of ſmall diſcretion, and fooliſh raſheneſſe. As though we ſhoulde bee an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grye with Fortune, becauſe we cannot ſhoote an arrowe out of a plowe, or hunt the Hare with an oxe, &amp; as though ſome vniuſt god did hinder thoſe that vainlye
<pb facs="tcp:176515:52"/> wente aboute to hunte the Harte in cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riottes, and not to bee rather angry with oure owne madneſſe and foolyſhneſſe in attempting to bryng to paſſe thinges vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſyble. The cauſe of this erroure, is none other, but onely ſelfe loue, for why<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt menne that loue themſelues to much: dooe attribute with greate comparyſon, the chiefeſt honour in all places to theym ſelues: they waxe ſo headye and ſo ſtub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burne, that they leaue no enterpriſe vnat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempted. Nor it is not ynoughe for them to be ritch, eloquente and pleaſaunt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paignions at the boord, yea to be frended with kinges, to beare rule and office, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept they maye haue alſo the beſt dogges, the faireſt horſes, cockes, &amp; quayles, with other like birdes of pleaſure, for els they can neuer bee quiete in minde. Dioniſius thelder was not contented to be the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt and moſt mightie Tiraunt that was in his time, but thinking it al to litle and far vnworthy his eſtate, becauſe he was not alſo ſo good in vercefying as Philoxe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nus the Poet, nor ſo eloque<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t as Plato: he
<pb facs="tcp:176515:52"/> was moued thereby to wrathe whiche o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uercame him. And therefore he baniſhed Philoxenus into Latumias &amp; ſent Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to to be ſold in Aegina. But Alexa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der did not ſo, at ſuch time as he contended with Briſon, whoſe chariot ſhould runne ſwif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt, for (thei ſay) he was highly diſpleaſed with Briſon, becauſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Briſon to flatter him did not his beſt, but ſuffered hym to win the race. Wherefore Homer ſpeaking of Achilles and Vliſſes, did verye well to geue eache manne his due prayſe in this wiſe.</p>
                  <q>
                     <l>Of all the greekes there was not one</l>
                     <l>In chiualrye that could him paſſe</l>
                     <l>But lawe to pleade ſuche one there was</l>
                     <l>As hym excelde who was alone.</l>
                  </q>
                  <p>Megabiſus perſes co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming on a time in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Apelles ſhoppe began to talke I know not what of the arte of paynctyng whoſe vnſkylfull pratynge Apelles not ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring: ſayde thus vnto him. Before that thou dyddeſte vtter thy ſelfe by thy talke, wee hadde ſomme good oppynion of thee, beecauſe thy garmentes of Golde
<pb facs="tcp:176515:53"/> and purple did beautify and ſet furth thy ſilence. But nowe the very boyes of my ſhoppe whiche grinde my coolours, dooe laughe at theſe thy foolyſhe bablynges. Some thinke that the Stoykes do mock vs, for that they doe not onely conſtitute and ordaine their wiſeman (whiche they faine vnto themſelues) to be prudent, iuſt, and valyaunt, but alſo they call hym an Oratour, an Emperoure, a Poet, and fy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally a kinge, and yet theſe glorious men aboueſaide, be not aſhamed to attrybute al theſe names to themſelues. And if thei perceiue at lengthe that they cannot at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne to them all: they bee immediatelye greued, and dooe take it verye heauelye, Whiche thing how reaſonable it is, thei themſelues may eaſily ſee. Sythe they knowe that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> goddes themſelues bee co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tente eache one, with his peculier and ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry name. As this god becauſe he hath y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> rule of warre and battayle, is ſurnamed Emialius, and that other becauſe he is God of prophecies, Mantous, &amp; another for that he is God of gayne and lucre
<pb facs="tcp:176515:53"/> Cerdous. Wherfore you ſhall read in Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, howe that Iupiter forbad Venus to intermedle with warrelyke affayres as thinges not appertayninge vnto her, and commanded her to take cure and charge onely of matters of weddyng, of bedding, and of pleaſure. Beſide this ſome of thoſe thinges whiche ſeeme woorthie to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired of vs, are of a contrary nature one to another. As for example it behoueth hym that endeuoureth himſelfe to ſtudye elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, or any other of the liberal ſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces, to be quiet and free from all worldlye af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires. For office in the citie, and the fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of kinges, are woont to cauſe muche buſineſſe, and often to cal away the mind from his determinate purpoſe. Alſo the aboundaunt vſe of wine and fleſhe, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth the body ſtrong and mete to wraſtle, but it maketh the mynde weake &amp; frayle. Finally in gathering and heaping vp of riches, a man muſt vſe great diligence te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe them, and as great carefulneſſe in kepyng them. Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trarywiſe the deſpiſing of them, and to ſet nought by them, is a
<pb facs="tcp:176515:54"/> great helpe and furtheraunce towardes the ſtudye of Philoſophy and as it were the firſt practiſing of theſame. Wherfore al men cannot haue al thinges. And ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it behoueth euery man tobay the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptes of Pittachus, that therby he may learne to knowe himſelf, and ſo to conſult with nature, &amp; to folow her as his guide, by applying himſelf to ſome one certayne thing, rather then by paſſing from one kinde of life vnto an other, to force nature. The horſe is mete for the cart, the oxe for the plowe, the Dollphin for the ſhip, and the fierce maſtife for the wilde bore. For if a manne would be grieued becauſe the mightye ſtronge Lyon cannot bee lyke a litle fawnyng dogge daintelye fedde in a widdowes lappe: truelye he myghte bee wel compted for a very foole. And he like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyſe ſhoulde not one whit be better, that would take vppon him bothe at one time to wryte of the worlde, and to ſearche oute the naturall cauſes of thynges, lyke as Empedocles, Plato, or Democritus dyd: as alſo attende to embrace an olde
<pb facs="tcp:176515:54"/> woman for rycheſſe ſake as Euphorion dydde. Or elles would bee like vnto thoſe that were wonte to ſpende the moſt part of the nyghte in bankettyng and reueling with Alexander, as Medius did, and yet to thynk ſuch pleſure to be nothing at al, except for rycheſſe he myghte bee alſo no leſſe notable then Iſmenia, and for ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, no leſſe famouſe then Epaminondas. Thoſe that runne for the beſte game, bee content with theyr rewarde, and dooe eaſilye ſuffer the wreſtlers to enioye to theymſelues, thoſe Crownes of glorye that they haue wonne. Haſte thou got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten Sparta (ſayeth Solon) to bee thy Countrey? then adourne it wyth good lawes and ordynaunces. But we would not (ſayeth the ſame Solon) chaunge with you oure vertue for youre richeſſe. For vertue is a ſtable thynge, and the propertye thereof maye bee poſſeſſed. But rycheſſe are onelye graunted too mannes vſe for a time, paſſinge oft from one to another. Strato the naturall Phyloſopher, when hee hearde that
<pb facs="tcp:176515:55"/> Meuedemus had more ſcholers then he: ſaid, is it ſo muche to be maruayled at, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> more deſier to bee waſhed then to bee an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nointed? Ariſtotle writinge to Antipater ſaid, that Alexa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der was much to be prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and extolled, not onely for that he had the rule and empire ouer manye nacions: but alſo for that he had a better opinion then others of thinges appertaignyng to god. And therfore if men would thus per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade with themſelues that theyr owne things ought to be reioyced in, to be prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and not to be ſo litle ſet by: thei ſhould not ſo pine away, in maruailyng at other men. But nowe though there bee none of vs al that thinketh the vine mete to beare figges, nor the olyue tree to brynge foorth grapes: yet do we continually accuſe our ſelues, and with vnthankful ſatiablenes vexe and greue our ſelues, yea we be we<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of our ſelues except we maie bee chief, ſo well amongſt the riche as alſo among thelloquent, at whom in peace, as abrode in warre, aſwel amongſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Philoſophers as the ſouldiers, and againe amongſt the
<pb facs="tcp:176515:55"/> flatterers, as amongſt thoſe that be true, and of a faithfull free ſimplicitie, and fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally ſo well amongeſt the couetous ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers, and as the prodigall ſpenders. And yet we ſee with oure eyes howe maruay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſly well nature dothe teache vs y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary. For as nature hathe ordeyned ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry wyld beaſtes to lyue by ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dry kindes of foode, and not to bee all fed either with ſeedes, fleſhe, or rootes, but diuers to eate of diuerſe meates: euen ſo likewiſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſelfe ſame nature hath geuen to mankind dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſe kindes of life, as ſome to be herdme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſome plowme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſome foulers, and ſome fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhers, wherefore it behoueth euery one of vs to take y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> whiche we perceiue is moſte meete for vs, and wholye applyinge oure ſelues to that, to depart from the poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of thoſe thynges, whiche we know do apperteigne to others. For otherwiſe He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiodus ſhould be vnwiſe to ſpeake in this ſorte.</p>
                  <q>
                     <l>The potter doth himſelf with potters aye compare</l>
                     <l>And eke the ſmith his like in arte texcell dothe care.</l>
                  </q>
                  <p>But nowe menne doe not contende one
<pb facs="tcp:176515:56"/> with another in lykeneſſe of arte or facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, but the riche with the eloquente, the nobles with the riche, and the lawyers with the ſubtile ſophiſters. Yea, free me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, gentlemen, and ſuche as bee deſcended of an auncient ſtocke, bee amaſed and dooe maruaile ſo muche at the good ſucceſſe &amp; promocion, that manye tymes players of merye interludes and commodies on ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, tumblers, and ſlaues, haue in kinges courtes, that whileſt thei thinke all their owne honeſt qualities not to be eſtemed: they vexe themſelues with great grieffes and ſorowfulneſſe of mynde, whiche at length dothe kyll them. But howe euerye man hath in his own mynde a ſtorehouſe or receptacle, and as it were a flowynge fountayne both of quietneſſe and of care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe, and hathe alſo the veſſels (wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of Homer ſpeaketh) full of all kynde of good and euyll, not as hee ſayeth, layde at Iupyter hys Doore, but placed wythin the ſoule: the dyuerſityes of menne, whiche wee ſee to bee dyuerſlye ruled by affections of the mynde dooe
<pb facs="tcp:176515:56"/> ryghte well declare. For fooles doe not onely paſſe ouer good thynges whiche be preſente, but alſo dooe neglect thoſe that bee paſte. So muche are theyr carefull myndes bente to that whiche is to come. But wiſe menne contrarywiſe reuoluing thynges throughe good remembraunce before their eyes, doe cauſe thoſe thinges that as yet bee not, to bee at hande, yea and to bee preſente in deede. Whereas to fooles (becauſe thynges preſent do chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce in a momente, ſo ſodainelye as they can not almoſte bee perceyued) it ſemeth that we haue nothynge nor that anye thynge apperteigneth vnto vs. And as the Rope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maker whiche is paincted in Pluto hys Temple, for ſlouth ſuffreth his Aſſe that ſtandeth by hym, to eate vp all the corde that hee of hempe hathe twyſted: euen ſo the vngratefull and ſluggiſhe forget<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe of manye, takynge awaye the commodyties receyued of thinges paſt, and cancellynge all the noble actes and woorthye enterpryſes, all the ſweete tyme ſpente in quyete Studye,
<pb facs="tcp:176515:57"/> free from all worldly affaires, all the ple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaunt and merie ſocieties and felow lyke liuynge together of frendes, and finallye cleane aboliſhyng all that parte of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lyfe, that euer was geuen to anye myrthe or pleaſure, wyll not ſuffer (I ſaye) one ſelf life to be made and knit of thynges paſte and preſent: but by ſeperatyng y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> life paſt, from the lyfe preſent, and agayne the lyfe preſent from the lyfe to come, maketh for lacke of callyng ſuche thinges to remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braunce all thinges to ſeeme, as though they had neuer bene done. Thoſe that in the ſcholles of Philoſophers doe take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way thencreaſe of bodies, affirmyng the ſubſtaunce to vaniſh away by continuall waſting of breath, doo ſeme to proue that euerye one of vs dooe alter ſtate of body &amp; dayly decay by woordes. But ſuche as do forgette thynges paſt, as though theyr memorie failed them, and will not repeat one thing often, thoſe do not in woordes, but in deedes make themſelues euery day more miſerable and poorer then other. Depending of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> time to come as thoughe
<pb facs="tcp:176515:57"/> thynges of a yere paſte and of late dayes, yea, and of yeſterdaye, apperteigned no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: yea, and as thoughe thoſe thinges hadde neuer chaunced vnto them. So that the quiet eſtate of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mind, is by this meanes diſturbed. And as flies creapyng vppon verye ſmoothe and ſlip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery glaſſe doe ſlide, and yet in rough and cranyed places doe eaſily ſticke: Euen ſo menne doe fal from merye and pleaſaunt thinges, and doe take ſure holde on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membraunce of heauye and ſorowefull thinges. Yea rather as by report, there is in Olinthios a certaine place called of the propertie thereof Cantharoletron, into the whiche when the great betleflyes bee once entered, they cannot fynde the waye out againe, but after that they haue ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny times tumbled to and fro and gone oft aboute in vaine, at length doe dye: ſo men being walowed into the remembrance of miſery &amp; aduerſitie, ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not afterward help themſelues out, nor yet once take breathe. And therfore as painters in their tables are wont with faire gliſtering coulours,
<pb facs="tcp:176515:58"/> to couer and to ouerlaye thoſe coulours that be duſkiſhe and not to be ſeen: So it behoueth menne in their myndes wyth thinges woorthye of remembraunce and praiſe, to preſſe down and to ouerwhelme all ſuche ſorowfull chaunces as are not to be ſpoken of. For thinges paſte cannot be vtterly abolyſhed nor yet dothe it lye in mannes power wholy to beware in time to come. For the armony of this world is ſo diuers and ſo variable as is the ſound of the harpe or viall. Neither doth manne poſſeſſe any thyng that is ſymple, ſincere or pure. But as muſicke is made of tunes high and lowe, and grammer of letters, whereof ſome bee vowelles, and ſome bee conſonauntes, and yet he is neither Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitian nor gramarian, that with either of theſe or thoſe wilbee offended, but rather that moſte aptlye can vſe them and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounde them bothe together: ſo he finally ſeemeth moſt wiſely to eſtabliſhe and dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recte his lyfe, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hath learned diſcretely to myngle together y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces &amp; ſucceſſes of thinges y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> be of diuers kindes, &amp; contrary
<pb facs="tcp:176515:58"/> one to another: by recompenſinge y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> haps vnfortunate, with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lucky and fortunate. For the commoditie of mans life will not ſuffer proſperitie and aduerſity to be put a ſunder eche one by himſelf, yea rather it behoueth vs, to make a certain te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>perature of them bothe, if we purpoſe to iudge and to determine of them rightly. Wherfore it is not mete to grunt or to grone at eyther of them, and to lye downe as one oppreſt with a heauye burthen for faintneſſe of hart and courage: but rather with the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of better happe, to withſtand and to beate back again the force and vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olence of euery vnlucky chaunce. And by couering the diſpleaſures and incommo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dityes, wyth the vayle clothe, of pleaſures and commodyties, to make the tenoure of the whole lyfe, beyng knytte and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacte of proſperitye and aduerſitie: lyke a certayne melodyous concorde tempered by art of muſick. Nor there is not (as Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nander thought) one au<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gel appointed to man ſo ſone as he is born to be y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> directer
<pb facs="tcp:176515:59"/> of his life, and as a mayſter to teache him to lyue well: but there be rather (as Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedocles ſaied) twoo aungelles and twoo ſundry fortunes, to whom he gaue many ſundrye names, whiche doo receaue vs al into their powere and tuycion ſo ſoone as we come into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world, being immediatly bounde and geuen vnto theim, with lyke lawe and condicion of ſeruitude. And he ſayde that in oure byrthe we receaue the ſeedes of al theſe affections. And therfore the waye of oure lyfe is not playne and ſmoothe, but roughe and full of harde paſſagies. For the whiche cauſe, the wiſe man wyſheth the beſt, and prouideth for the woorſte, and vſeth both temperatlye, aduoydynge in either parte all extremity. For it is not ſo (as Epicurus affirmeth) that he onelye with pleaſure approcheth the tyme to come, whiche careth not whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he lyue ſo long or not: but thoſe ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther receaue moſt pleaſure of riches, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, power, and dominion, which if nede ſhould bee, coulde take the contrary ſtate and condicion of lyfe in good worthe. For
<pb facs="tcp:176515:59"/> the vehemente deſier of anye thing is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies accompanied with a certain feare to loſe the ſame, whiche feare appaullith mans mirth and ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>times interrupteth the ſame, like a flame of fier reſtrained by a greater violence of winde. But that ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whom reaſon hath taught boldly wyth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out feare to ſpeake vnto Fortune in thys wiſe.</p>
                  <q>
                     <l>Like as tenioy thy giftes, I would be very glad</l>
                     <l>Euen ſo to loſe the ſame, I wilbe nothing ſad:</l>
                  </q>
                  <p>Muſt nedes I ſaie truſting in himſelf enioy thinges preſent with pleaſure, nor cannot be often vexte with feare, in reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bring of any loſſe that maye enſue. When Anaxagoras hearde that his ſonne was dead: he ſaide. when I did bigette hym I knewe well that he ſhoulde dye, &amp; to that end I brought him vp. This affeccio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naxagoras oughte aſwel to be folowed of vs, as to be maruailed at. For euerye one of vs, to anye miſhappe that chaunceth, maye immediately ſaie thus. I knewe right well, that the riches whiche I poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſe, were but lent me for a time, and not
<pb facs="tcp:176515:60"/> bounde to me by any neceſſity, and that I had but onely the vſe of them. And I was not ignoraunt that thei whiche gaue me power and aucthoritie, might alſo take it from me, if they liſte. I knewe my wyfe to be honeſt, and yet a woman alſo. And fy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally it was not hydde from me, that my frende was a man, whiche is a beaſte (as Plato ſayeth) whoſe nature wilbe eaſily corrupted. Truely he y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> will make compte of his affectes after this ſorte and wyll buylde before in his minde ſuche kynd of Bulwarkes and fortes of reaſon: though any thinge perhappes ſhall afterwarde chaunce againſt his deſyer or peruerſely: yet ſhall it not chaunce ſodaynlye or vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>looked for. Becauſe he wyll neuer ſaye (as the common ſorte dooeth) that I woulde neuer haue thought it, or that I hadde a better hope, thynkyng that this could ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer haue come ſo to paſſe. Yea ſuche a manne I ſaye, ſhall alwayes bee hable to putte away the waueryng of his hart, beatyng and quiuering for feare, and to brynge it by and by from trouble and
<pb facs="tcp:176515:60"/> vexacion, to reſte and quietneſſe. Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ades was wonte to putte menne moſte in remembraunce of aduerſitye, when they were in greateſt proſperitie. Bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that all thynges that come ſodain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye and vnlooked for: bee naturally apte to bee receyued with griefe and trouble of the mynde, and as it were with fain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tynge and ſoundyng. And nowe to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyrme that whiche hath bene ſayde with ſome exaumples. Fyrſt howe ſmal a por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion is Macedonye of the Romaine Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pyre? And yet when kynge Perſis hadde loſte it, he didde not crye out only of For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune with foule complaintes: but alſo ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to manye others to bee the myſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleſt manne and moſte vnfortunate that euer was. But beholde on the other ſyde Emilius, who departyng out of the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uynce, after that he had once vanquiſhed Perſis, and yelded vppe to his ſucceſſor all the rule and power that he had bothe by Sea and lande: was receyued wyth crownes of glorye and greate reioycing. For al men in the tyme of doing ſacrifice,
<pb facs="tcp:176515:61"/> did extoll him with praiſes vp to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uens, and that not vnworthely, yea moſte woorthely. For this man had alwayes in remembraunce, how that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Empire was geuen him but to vſe for a tyme. But Perſis contrarywiſe, was depryued of his kingdome by a ſodayne chaunce and vnlooked for. And truely it ſeemeth to me that Homer by a goodly exaumple hathe very well taught vs, howe muche more grieuous ſodayn ſtrokes be, then others. For Vliſſes beyng come home againe out of a ſtraunge countrey, wept to ſee the ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dayne deathe of his dogge. And yet ſyt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting by his lamentynge wife, didde not wepe at all. For he being many times to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes comming home, conceiued before in his mind, thimage of his weping wife. And ſo that affection whiche wythoute doubte, in a ſodaine woulde haue bruſte out: he by layſure ſubdued, and by harde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning his heart before, broughte it cleane vnder his rule and power. But he was ſomwhat troubled with the ſodein death of his dogge, becauſe that in ſo ſodayne a
<pb facs="tcp:176515:61"/> thing he hadde not tyme to reſtrayne the force of his affection. And to ſpeake brief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye, partlye ſuche thynges as chaunce o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe then we deſier: be intollerable &amp; grieuous to ſuffer by nature, and partly a corrupte oppinion and naughtye cuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome of oure ſelues hath taughte vs to be grieued therewith. And that is the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt parte, againſt the whiche, it ſhould be well done, to haue alwaies ready at hand this ſayinge of Menander. Thou neuer ſuffereſt any outragious thynge, excepte thou ſuppoſe it ſo to be. For what needeſt thou to care, ſo long as it pyncheth not thy fleſhe, nor toucheth thy lyfe, as for ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aumple. The lowe byrth of thy father, the whoredome of thy mother, to be depriued of the honour of the higheſt ſeate, or to be iniured, in that the glorie of the victory is taken from thee: what dooe theſe thinges I ſaye apperteigne to thee? For thoughe all theſe thynges were ſo in deede: yet nothynge letteth thee, but that thou ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yeſt bee well, yea and verye well dyſpoſed
<pb facs="tcp:176515:62"/> both of body and ſoule. Now againſt ſuch thinges as naturally ſomewhat offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d vs as ſicknes, miſery, &amp; death of oure fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des, we ought tobiect this ſayi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g, wo is we. But why woe is me ſyth we haue ſuffered no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, but that whiche apperteygneth to man. For there is no talke or ſaying, that doeth more quickly reproue the paſſyble parte of the ſoule, when it is drawen out of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> right waye by vnbrideled affections: then that ſayinge which doth admoniſhe vs, and put vs in remembraunce of the v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niuerſall and naturall neceſſitie, and of that which muſt nedes be, with the whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che neceſſitie man is noryſhed vppe and wrapt in it, at the tyme of his byrthe and fyrſt knyttynge of his bodye, whiche one knotte is onelye ſubiecte to fortunes aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaultes, and al the reſte of natures gyftes whiche be chiefeſt and of moſt valewe, he may ſafely poſſeſſe withoute daunger. When Kynge Demetrius had taken the cytie of Megara, it is ſayde that he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded Stylpo the Philoſopher, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb facs="tcp:176515:62"/> he hadde loſte anye of hys goodes or not? To whom Stylpo anſwered. That he ſawe no manne takynge awaye anye thynge of his, for (ſaieth he) though for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune hathe ſuffered vs to bee robbed and ſpoyled of all the reſte: yet wee haue ſome thynge lefte in vs, whiche the Greekes can neyther beare nor dryue awaye. It is no reaſon therefore, ſo muche to deſpyſe and to reiecte nature, as though ſhe had no iote of fortitude nor of ſufferaunce and therefore not equall in force, to Fortune. But ſythe wee knowe ryghte well that, that parte of manne which is to fortune ſubiecte, is a verye ſmall porcion of vs, and lytle to bee regarded, beyng ſo brittle and ſo ſofte that it yeldeth at the fyrſte to euery lytle pouſhe: and that we be lordes of the better parte, wherein as in a ſtrong holde all good thynges be placed: yea, and wherein alſo, true glorye, ſcy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences, and all ſtudies apperteigninge to vertue haue their beyng: whiche cannot be taken awaie nor euer periſhe by anye
<pb facs="tcp:176515:63"/> vyolence: it becommeth vs (I ſaye there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore) to bee in mynde vnuincible, and to truſte in oure ſelues, fearynge nothynge that is to come. And to ſaye to fortune, that whiche Socrates fainynge to haue ſpoken vnto Anitus and Melitus his ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſours, ſpake in deede to the Iudgies. Anitus and Melitus maye well take my life from me, but hurt or damage thei can do me none. For though Fortune may op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe manne with diuers dyſeaſes de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroye his goodes, and accuſe him to the Tiraunte, or to the people, yet ſhe cannot make hym an euyll manne, or a cowarde, or falſe hearted and faynte of courage or malicious, and ſpecially he beyng a good manne, and endued with manlyneſſe and ſtouteneſſe of courage. And finally ſhe can not take away the right conſtitucion and diſpoſicion of the mind, whiche doth help manne more to paſſe his lyfe, then thart of ſailing doeth the mariner to paſſe the ſeas. For the ſterne man be he neuer ſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pert, can no more ſtil the raging ſea or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe the violence of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> boyſterous winds,
<pb facs="tcp:176515:63"/> then to take hauen where as he liſt, ſo oft as he deſireth to come from ſea to ſhore. No nor yet ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his art performe this, that he being taken in a ſodain tempeſt maye co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtantly and without feare eſcape ſuch neceſſity. But onely it helpeth thus much that ſo long as he deſpaireth not but that arte maie take place, he gathereth in hys ſayles aſwel as he ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and ſo floteth with the tempeſt, wheras the cowardly mary<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner ſitteth wryngynge his handes toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and whilſte the maſte of the ſhip ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth drowned by violence of windes in the ſea, he trembleth &amp; quaketh for feare. But the quiet mind in a wiſeman, both bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth healthe to the bodye by the meanes of continency, good diete &amp; exerciſe (whyche thinges dooe aſwage and cleane take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waye the cauſe and matter of ſickneſſe) &amp; alſo if there be afterward perhappes any occaſion of trouble whereuppon mannes mind doth run as vpon a rocke in the ſea: he hoyſeth vp ſayle, and as (Eſclapiades ſaith) quickly paſſeth theſame. But fooles not ſo muche for deſier of life as for feare
<pb facs="tcp:176515:64"/> of deathe, dooe hang on the bodye by the hands cloſed lattys wiſe one finger with in another: eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as Vliſſes did hang by the wild figge tree when he feared y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous goulfe called Caribdis roaringe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneath him, who (as Homer writeth) be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing ſodainly taken in the ſea of Sycelye, was brought to ſuch caſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> by meanes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> violence of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> winde driuing him hither &amp; thither, he could nether go forward nor backward, nor yet as the prouerbe ſaieth, as one y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> holdeth a wolf by the eares: was hable what for wearines, &amp; for thu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomnes of the place, to holde the tree any lenger, and yet durſt not let it go for feare of the terrible monſter. Truely if a man woulde by ſome meanes ſearche oute the nature of oure ſoule, and think with him ſelfe, that by death we paſſe from this life to a better, or at the leaſt not to a woorſe: certainly that man in deſpiſinge deathe, ſhoulde prepare for himſelfe no ſmal pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſion, to conduct him in his iourney to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes the quietneſſe and tranquilitye of the mynde. For he that as well by force
<pb facs="tcp:176515:64"/> of vertue whiche is proper and peculyer to manne, may liue pleaſantly, as alſo by meanes of other thinges not apperteyg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng to manne, but geuen beſides nature being of great power &amp; farre paſſing our own proper thinges: maie be of ſuch bold ſpirite and courage, that he maie ſaye to himſelf, I maie depart, yea I ſaye eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> at the firſte inſtant, and by gods leaue whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I will my ſelfe: Howe I pray you, or whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> maie we thinke that any grieuous thing indiſſoluble or troublous, can chaunce to this man? But whoſoeuer he was y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fyrſt ſpake this famous and renowmed ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, O Fortune I haue preuented thee, and taken vppe before all thy wayes and paſſages bee they neuer ſo ſtrayghte: truelye that manne ſeemeth not to haue encouraged and boldned himſelf by ſtrong buildings faſt barred and ſurelye locked: but rather by Philoſophicall decrees and teſtimoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es of wiſe men which be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon and eaſie for all menne to haue, yea and readie at hande to all thoſe that ſhall vouche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafe to receaue them. Neyther oughte
<pb facs="tcp:176515:65"/> we to take awaye our credite from ſuche thinges as be conſecrated to the memorie of vs &amp; of our poſteritie, nor yet to diſpair or to miſtruſt our ſelues as vnhable euer to folow any parte thereof. But as wee ought to haue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in admiracion, &amp; as it were by a certain inſpiration of god to be amaſed at the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: ſo alſo it behoueth hym y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> prepareth himſelf to folowe theſame, too make ſuch a ſhowe of himſelfe that in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning firſt with ſmal thinges, he maye afterwarde attempt greater and greater, &amp; ſo at le<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth atchieue to the higheſt. But we muſt take hede in ani wiſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we forget not to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider theſe thyngs before, nor yet be greued to reuolue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in our mind &amp; to think of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with all our hart, whych thyng is not, vneaſy to be done. For as the dilicatenes of the minde, whych being oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupied in euery litle trifle and thinges of ſmal weight, is woont by a naughty ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feraunce to withdraw it ſelf from vnple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaunt thinges for to folow things of ple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure: dothe annoy vs and infect vs with a certain ſlouthful diliciouſnes &amp; te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dernes:
<pb facs="tcp:176515:65"/> euen ſo, if a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> would behold in his mind thimage of ſicknes, labor, trauail, baniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, &amp; ſuch other like, &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maund in him ſelf the force of his wit &amp; reaſon, diligent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to diſcuſſe eache thing y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is to be ponde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by it ſelf: that ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, I ſay, with out doubt, ſhould quickly find thoſe thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges that ſeme greuous &amp; horrible, to be in dede vain &amp; for the moſt part not to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garded, and finally to threaten more out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thei can performe inwardly. But the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon ſort doe feare this ſaying of Menander. There is no man that may glory ſo muche of himſelfe in his lyfe time as to ſaye, that I wyll not ſuffer this, or that. And no maruayle why, ſythe they knowe not howe muche it helpeth towardes thad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoiding of heauines, taccuſtom the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues to behold fortune with a froward counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, &amp; with a fierce looke, &amp; not to be ge<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uen to effeminate thoughtes &amp; wauering delites, which being nouriſhed in darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, &amp; abaſhed at euery gliſtering light of hope, do yeld to euery trifle. Albeit Mena<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der might be anſwered thus. A ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ought
<pb facs="tcp:176515:66"/> not to ſay, I wil not in my life time ſuffer this, but rather ought to ſaie, I wyll not whilſt I liue do this. As I wil not lye, I wil not vſe ſubtil craft in deceauing men, I will not defraude them of their ryght, I will not maliciouſlye lay waite to take them in a trap. For ſithe this thing conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteth in our power, it muſt nedes be a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry great helpe to thoſe that do further the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues tobteigne quietnes of minde. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarywiſe a wicked conſcience is in the ſoule, like a wounde in the bodie, &amp; it cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth repentance, which continually fret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth and tormenteth the ſoule. For where as reaſon is wont to take away all other griefes and heauines, this naughtie con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience (I ſaie) cauſeth repentaunce for ſhame to prouoke it ſelfe of the owne ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corde, and as it were eagerlye to byte and to teare it ſelfe in pieces. And as the colde of a colde ague, or the heate of a burnynge feauoure dooeth muche more vehementlye and grieuouſlye afflicte the bodye, then anye other outwarde heate or colde. Euen ſo the griefes and ſorowes
<pb facs="tcp:176515:66"/> that come vnto vs by chaunce, be eaſier to ſuffer, then thoſe that by our owne folye dooe breede in oure ſelues. This ſayinge alſo which euery man whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he hath done any miſchief is wont with weaping tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res to howle out. There is no manne to bee blamed for thys, but I my ſelfe: maketh the wounde whiche is greuous of it ſelfe, muche more greuous and dothe pearce it deper. For neyther goodlye buyldynges, nor aboundaunce of golde, nor yet noble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of byrthe or great Empire, nor fy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nallye, pleaſaunt ſpeache, eloquence, or promptnes of tounge, can brynge ſuche ſtylneſſe and pleaſaunt quietneſſe of lyfe, as the mynde that is free from penſyue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and lyueth by it ſelfe, farre of, from wycked thoughtes. Whiche mynde ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyng in it ſelf a cleare and pure fountain of lyfe (whereby I meane an honeſt dyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition and vertuous behauyoure from whence all commendable doynges dooe ſpring) as a thing encouraged I ſaye by ſome inſpiracio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of god, doth bringe furth all her doinges in myrthe and pleaſure,
<pb facs="tcp:176515:67"/> with the continuall reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>brance whereof ſhe is onely fed, being to her a great deale ſweter &amp; much more aſſured, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the hope wherof Pyndarus ſpeaketh, which (as he ſaith) dothe nouriſhe olde age. And as the ſwete gardein plots (as Carneades was wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to ſay) though thei be ſpoiled of their pleaſant ſhrubbes, the rootes being cut or pulled vp, do yeld for al y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a certain ſweete ſmel lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g time after: eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo honeſt doings, do leaue in the mind of a wyſeman, a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>brance which is alwaies plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant &amp; freſhe. With the which reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>brance y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> inward mirth being watered, as it wer wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>h a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinual ru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ning brooke, is alwais greene &amp; bringeth furth yonge ſhootes &amp; ſpringes to the great ſhame of thoſe that do oft lame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t &amp; blame this lyfe, affirminge it to be a counſel houſe of miſchief, &amp; a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain aſſemble of baniſhed folkes, into the which the ſoules be ſent a way fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> aboue, as though thei wer baniſhed out of their countrey. Truely I cannot but iudge this ſaying of Diogenes moſte worthy of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membraunce. Who eſpying a ſtranger on
<pb facs="tcp:176515:67"/> a time in Lacedemony gorgeouſly array<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing himſelf againſt a feſtiuall daie, ſayde thus, what (quoth he?) Is not euery daye to a good man a feſtiuall daie? yes truely (if we conſider thinges wel) moſt feſtiuall &amp; ioyful. For the world is no other thyng but a holy temple, &amp; moſte meete for God. And into this temple, man at his byrthe tyme is admitted, not to beholde ymages made by mans hand, &amp; withoute ſence or feling: but to behold the Su<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Moone, &amp; the Starres, from whence our life toke her firſt beginni<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g &amp; mouing, which thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges the prouidence of god gaue vs to bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, to thentent y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſuch thinges as be ſub<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>iect to the outward ſences, mighte bee (as Plato ſaith) ymages &amp; examples of thoſe thinges which are to be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>prehended and vnderſtanded by the minde. Adde hereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the floudes continually bringing freſh water and earth, which nouriſheth bothe plant &amp; beaſt. It behoueth our lyfe there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, that wil truelye beginne to celebrate this noble feaſt &amp; goodly ſight, to be ful of mirthe &amp; quietnes. And not to tarie for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
                     <pb facs="tcp:176515:68"/> feaſte of Saturne, of Bacchus or of Pallas (as many doe) whiche dooe abyde theſe and ſuche other feaſtyuall dayes when they approche with greate expec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tacion, and fynallye beynge come they receaue them and the playes celebrated in the ſame, with much reioyceing. And for their pleaſures ſake, they paie alſo hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to players of Interludes, to Minſtrels and to Tu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>blers, that in thoſe daies they maie delyght themſelues, the more wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonly with bought mirthe. But what ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> bee a more vndecent thing then this, that during ſuche playes, we can ſit quietly, kepinge a maruaylous ſtyll ſylence, at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendynge to nothynge but to that one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye. For neyther dooeth any manne la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mente whylſte hee dooeth Sacryfyce, nor yet whylſte hee beholdeth the plaies of Apollo, no more then hee that ſyt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth at Saturnes feaſte, complayneth for hunger. And yet ſuche ſolempne feaſtes, as God is aucthour of, and as it were rynge leader, we manye tymes
<pb facs="tcp:176515:68"/> defyle and vyolate, by paſſynge theym ouer with lamentynge, wyth bitterneſſe of hearte, and wyth myſerable lyuyng. And thys alſo is verye vnſeemelye for vs to bee delyghted wyth the melodious noyſe of Organes, and with the ſwete ſyngynge of byrdes, and wyllynglye to beholde beaſtes whylſte they playe to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, and leape too and fro. And a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayne to bee offended wyth theyr loude howlynge, terryble roarynge, and cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ell lookynge. And yet we ſeynge oure owne ſorowfull heauye and frowarde lyfe, drowned in noyſome affectes, in troubles and cares inexplycable, be not onelye vnhable to craue caſemente for oure ſelues and ſpace to breathe: But alſo vnwilling to heare thoſe that would exhorte vs thereunto. To whoſe ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monyſhmentes if with eares vnoccupied and wel pourged we would attende, we<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſhould both vſe thinges preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t according as they bee, withoute feare of reproofe,
<pb facs="tcp:176515:69" rendition="simple:additions"/> and alſo wee ſhoulde quiete oure ſelues wythe pleaſaunt remembraunce of thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges paſte. And finally hauynge an aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured and ioyfull hope alwayes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore oure eyes, wee ſhould bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly aproche thynges that are to come.</p>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
      </group>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>¶ Imprinted at London by Wylliam Seres dwellyng at the Weſt end of Poules at the Sygne of the Hedgehogge, the vii. daye of Iune. An. domini. 1561.</p>
            <p>¶ Cum priuilegio ad im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>primendum ſolum</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:176515:69"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
